<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A true interpretation of the VVitch of Endor spoken of in I Sam. 28, begin. at the ll. verse ... / by Lodowick Muggleton.</title>
            <author>Muggleton, Lodowick, 1609-1698.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1669</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 121 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 47 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A51581</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M3051</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R7476</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13236750</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13236750</idno>
            <idno type="VID">98607</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A51581)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 98607)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 429:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A true interpretation of the VVitch of Endor spoken of in I Sam. 28, begin. at the ll. verse ... / by Lodowick Muggleton.</title>
                  <author>Muggleton, Lodowick, 1609-1698.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 54 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1669.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signature A is missing; p. 4 is stained; p. 11-12 are torn with print missing in filmed copy. Beginning-p. 19 photographed from Huntington Library copy and inserted at the end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Witch of Endor --  (Biblical figure)</term>
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Samuel, 1st, XXVIII, 11 --  Criticism, interpretation, etc.</term>
               <term>Witchcraft --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Soul --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:98607:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98607:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98607:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98607:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98607:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98607:5"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98607:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98607:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98607:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98607:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98607:36" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98607:36"/>
            <p>A TRUE INTERPRETATJON Of the VVitch of Endor.</p>
            <p>Spoken of in 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 28. begin. at the 11. Verſe; Shewing,</p>
            <p n="1">1. How She and all other Witches do beget or produce that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar ſpirit they deal with, and what a familiar ſpirit is, and how thoſe Voices are procured, and Shapes appear unto them, whereby the ignorant and unbelieving people are deceived by them.</p>
            <p>It is clearly made appear in this Treatiſe, that no ſpirit can be raiſed without its body, neither can any ſpirit aſſume any body after death; for if the ſpirit doth walk, the body muſt walk alſo.</p>
            <p n="3">3. An Interpretation all thoſe Scriptures, that doth ſeem as if ſpirits might go out of mens bodies when they die, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt in ſome place or other without bodies.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, Several other things needful for the mind of man to know; which whoever doth underſtand it will be great ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction.</p>
            <p>By LODOWICK MUGGLETON.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year 1669.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:98607:37"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98607:37"/>
            <head>TO THE Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Have been deſired by ſeveral Friends to ſet forth the In<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation concerning the Witch of <hi>Endor,</hi> and King <hi>Saul,</hi> how it may be underſtood how ſhe raiſed <hi>Samuel,</hi> and how familiar ſpirits came to be procured, and with what power they do ſuch ſtrange things; Many Enemies alſo have objected this place, to prove that ſpirits may be raiſed without Bodies, and that ſpirits may walk, or be happy or miſerable without bodies: though I have given Anſwer in diſcourſe to theſe Doubts and Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions, but few can retain in their memory what is ſpoken in Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe; therefore I thought it convenient and neceſſary to ſet it forth in Print, for the Information and Satisfaction of many friends who deſire it, and for the Convincement of all Gain-ſayers; and let them ſeriouſly read it over without prejudice, and they may ſee this Point clearly opened, which hath layn hid this many hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred years, with other Places of Scriptures opened, which man<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> have objected againſt this Interpretation, and all th ſe places of Scripture that is commonly brought, or doth moſt ſeem to hold forth that ſpirits may he without bodies, are likewiſe opened and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded in ſhort in this Treatiſe, as followeth.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:98607:8"/>
            <head>I. SAM. XXVIII. from the 11, to the 18. Verſe.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Shall give the Interpretation, what is meant by that familiar ſpirit the Witch of <hi>Endor</hi> did raiſe <hi>Samuel</hi> by, ſo much ſpoken of in the book of <hi>Samuel</hi> and o her places of Scripture, and ſo much objected by many to prove that ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits may be raiſed without bodies, and may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear unto people in what ſhape they pleaſe.</p>
               <p>The belief of this lying principle, it did proceed out of the imagination of reaſon, the devil—the Imagination that doth ariſe or proceed from the ſeed of reaſon in man, is that familiar ſpirit that Witches deal with, and that familiar ſpirit it proceedeth from no ſpirit or devil without a man, but from the ſeed of reaſon within man; for look what evil thoughts doth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe out of the heart of man, it proceedeth out of the ſeed of reaſon in man, and not from any thing without man; for the imagination of the heart, it is placed in the ſeed of reaſon, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is ſaid in Scripture, <hi>That the imaginations of mans heart was evil, and that every imaginations of the thoughts of his heart was only evil continually,</hi> as in <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.5. ſo that there is no other devil, or ſpirit, or familiar ſpirit for Witches to deal withal, or to work any Enchantments by, but their own imagination, there the familiar ſpirit is produced from whence it came; and there it ceaſes to be when they are put to death; or over-powered by the knowledge and power of faith in other men; then the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar ſpirit centers in the imagination again, it being overpow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ered by the power of faith; ſo likewiſe the good thoughts that doth proceed out of the heart of man, they do ariſe or proceed from the ſeed of faith, concerning the true God, or any heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſecret, or temporal judgements, or temporal bleſſings, if the foreknowledge of theſe things doth ariſe or be foretold by the revelation of the ſeed of faith, they are and may be called the Spirit of God.</p>
               <p>Becauſe they were foretold and declared by the revelation of the ſeed of faith, which ſeed of faith is the ſeed of God, it being
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:98607:9"/>
of Gods own Nature, therefore called the Spirit of God, and ſo foretold and declared by the Spirit of God; ſo likewiſe what foreknowledge or declaration of things, that are above that which is common to the ſeed of reaſon, (as raiſing of ſpirits and ſuch like;) <hi>I</hi> ſay, they do proceed from the imagination of reaſon the devil; and this ſtrong imagination from the ſeed of of reaſon, is that familiar ſpirit by which Witches do divine or foretel things; ſo that the ſtrong imagination of reaſon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing exerciſed about things that are beyond Trades and Sciences, that are neceſſary needful and lawful, ſo it becomes a familiar ſpirit becauſe it proceeds from the imagination of reaſon, and the ſeed of reaſon being the devil, and the devil being the fallen Angel; for the devil is man and woman, and the ſeed of reaſon is their ſeed: and that eed of reaſon it came from that ſerpent that beguiled <hi>Eve,</hi> and that ſerpent was an Angel, and his ſeed was reaſon, and this reaſon in man is the devil, and the imagination of reaſon is the father of that familiar ſpirit by which a man or woman doth divine, ſoothſay, raiſe ſhapes, or hear voices, or any ſuch thing of that nature, they all proceed from the imagination of reaſon in man, and the original being of this ſeed of reaſon; it came from that Serpent-Angel, that was caſt down from Heaven unto this Earth, who deceived our firſt Parents, as <hi>I</hi> have abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly ſhewed in <hi>Rev.</hi> 11. and in the interpretation of the whole Book of the Revelation.</p>
               <p>Now <hi>I</hi> have laid a Foundation for the Reader, that he may the better underſtand the Foundation, from whence theſe familiar ſpirits that Witches have, do proceed, and how they are procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and what power they have over the ignorant mind of man, Therefore to ſatisfie the thoughts of many, who hath deſired and requeſted of me that I would interpret ſome chief ſayings in the Scriptures, that ſpeaketh of Witchcraft, and familiar ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits and ſuch like, which ſayings are very ſtrange and hard to be underſtood, ſo that moſt people are very much unſatisfied in theſe things, though clear in their Judgements in many other things that are of more concernment; and as <hi>I</hi> have given the Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation of the whole Book of the <hi>Revelation,</hi> with many other places of Scripture, to the great comfort and ſatisfaction of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, ſo <hi>I</hi> ſhall adde the Interpretation of this thing alſo.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:98607:9"/>The firſt place of Scripture I ſhall inſiſt upon is, that in 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 28. beginning at the 11. verſe, concerning the Witch of <hi>Endor;</hi> this is commonly the place that moſt people fetch to prove that ſpirits may be raiſed in what ſhape the Witch pleaſe by their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar ſpirits; therefore let the Reader mind the diſcourſe that followeth.</p>
               <p>The words are theſe, <hi>Then ſaid the Woman, Whom ſhall I bring up unto thee? and he ſaid, bring me up</hi> Samuel; and in the 12. verſe; <hi>And when the Woman ſaw</hi> Samuel; <hi>ſhe cried with a loud voice, and the Woman ſpake to</hi> Saul, <hi>ſaying, why haſt thou deceived me, for thou art</hi> Saul; and in the 13. verſe, <hi>And the King ſaid unto her, be not afraid, for what ſaweſt thou? and the Woman ſaid unto</hi> Saul, <hi>I ſaw Gods aſcending out of the Earth;</hi> the 14. verſe, <hi>And he ſaid unto her, what form is he of? and ſhe ſaid, an old man cometh up, and he is covered with a mantle, and</hi> Saul <hi>perceived it was</hi> Samuel, <hi>and he ſtooped with his face to the ground, and bowed himſelf,</hi> the 15. verſe, <hi>And</hi> Samuel <hi>ſaid to</hi> Saul, <hi>why haſt thou diſquieted me to bring me up; And</hi> Saul <hi>anſwered, I am ſore di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed, for the</hi> Philiſtines <hi>make war againſt me, and God is depart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from me, and anſwereth me no more, neither by Prophet, nor by Dreams; therefore</hi> I <hi>have called thee that thou mayſt make known unto me what I ſhall do;</hi> verſe 16. <hi>Then ſaid</hi> Samuel, <hi>Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore then doſt thou ask of me, ſeeing the Lord is departed from thee, and is become thine enemie;</hi> verſe 17. <hi>And the Lord hath done to him, as he ſpake by me, for the Lord hath rent the Kingdom out of thine hand, and given it to thy neighbour, even to</hi> David; verſe 18. <hi>becauſe thou obeyeſt not the Voice of the Lord, nor executed his fierce wrath upon</hi> Amalek, <hi>therefore hath the Lord done this thing unto thee this day.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <p>THis familiar ſpirit the Witch of <hi>Endor</hi> and other Witches have, whereby they do ſuch things, it is the imagination of reaſon, the devil in themſelves; that is, they ſet themſelves a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part with the thoughts of the imaginations of their hearts, to dive into the diabolical power, that is, that they might know
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:98607:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
the depths of Satan, their imagination conceiving that the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil is a ſpirit flying in the air, and that this ſpirit can aſſume or take up any ſhape it pleaſe; ſo that the imagination of the heart hath produced an evil ſpirit in it ſelf, ſo that this familiar ſpirit is begotten out of the womb of reaſon; for the ſeed of reaſon in man is the womb or the mother; and the imagination of the heart is the father that begets this familiar ſpirit, and this fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar ſpirit is the ſon of imagination; ſo that all thoughts of the heart, and that wonderful knowledge declared, by them it is revealed through this ſon the familiar ſpirit begotten in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves by the ſeed of reaſon the mother, and imagination the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; ſo that there is no devil nor familias ſpirit without them, as people do vainly imagine, but the devil and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>liar ſpirit is all within them, and no where elſe; yet all people fear a devil without them, but he is no where to be found but in man and woman, this I do certainly know to be true.</p>
               <p>Again, theſe Witches doth ſuppoſe the true God to be an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ite ſpirit, without any body or ſubſtance, as all people a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap> do; and that the devil is a ſpirit that can aſſumeth bodies, or what ſhape he pleaſeth, or what ſhape or forme the Witch ſhall call for this, is the opinion of moſt people in the world, as well as Witch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, yea, even of the moſt of the greateſt learned men; darkneſs hath overſpread the minds of all learned men in the world, ſo that they cannot finde out what the true God is, nor where he is, nor what the right devil is, nor where he is; yea, man himſelf is he that cannot finde out himſelf; But no more of this now.</p>
               <p>To the matter in hand, the Witches they do not know any di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine being, or power, or forme of God; but what their imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation doth conceive to be God, for they have full faith in this knowledge of theirs, to be the true knowledge of God; only the Laws of men they fear, but no other God, but that familiar ſpirit which they have produced in themſelves, by giving them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves either to faſting and prayer, unto an unknown divine being or power, ſuppoſing this power to be a ſpirit that can appear in any ſhape they ſhall call for or deſire; and all people being igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of the true God, and the right devil, as they themſelves
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:98607:10"/>
are ſo that the people have a faith in theſe Witches, being ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant as aforeſaid.</p>
               <p>What the true God and right devil is, and the Witches faith and their faith being joyned together, it becometh ſtrong to atchieve ſuch appriſions as their faith hath choſe to be the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of their imagination: for he that enquireth of a Witch, his faith and the Witches faith is all one.</p>
               <p>Alſo this is to be minded, that all Witches have ſome rule by which they do perceive thoſe Appriſions, and hear thoſe voices, for there is no wicked knowledg or wicked wiſdom as the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of the world, neither is there any good knowledge or good wiſdom as the wiſdom of God. I ſay, there is no knowledge or wiſdom good or bad, but thoſe that have it they muſt go by ſome rule, elſe it is meer nonſenſe as moſt of your Quakers Matters or Principles are meer nonſenſe, that hath neither bottom nor top.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <p>BUt to the matter in hand, we ſee that the natural Aſtrologers they go by a rule, and their wiſdom and knowledge in things of Nature, it is declared by them from and by a rule elſe that they ſay would be meer nonſenſe and fooliſhneſs.</p>
               <p>Yet <hi>I</hi> ſay, your natural Aſtrologers they are Witches, and have their Figure to judge the effects of the Stars; but this Witchcraft is allowed by the Powers of the Nations.</p>
               <p>So I ſay, theſe Witches that doth do things by a familiar ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, they have a rule to walk by as the other hath, for as the ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination of the other hath by his ſtudy of the Figure at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained to give ſome judgement upon the effects of the Stars, upon a particular perſon or Nation. So likewiſe thoſe Witches that hath a familiar ſpirit, they have attained to this familiar ſpirit out of their imagination of reaſon, as I ſaid before.</p>
               <p>And this familiar ſpirit being begotten in themſelves by the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:98607:11"/>
ſtrength of imagination their father; now underſtand thus much that this diabolical wiſdom that is begotten in man and woman by the imagination of reaſon, the devil is that familiar ſpirit that men and women do act by.</p>
               <p>And after this familiar ſpirit is begotten in man or woman by Imagination their father, as I ſaid before, then this familiar ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of the Witch will motion in the minde to faſt, and pray un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Hoſt of Heaven, the Sun, Moon and Planets, ſuppoſing that the good ſpirit is in ſome of them, and imagining the evil ſpirit or devil to be in other ſome of them.</p>
               <p>Now obſerve, when this familiar ſpirit is produced in them, then they obſerve every motion of the mind, and their faith be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in every motion of their minds, it produceth either ſome further knowledge in their own apprehenſion, or elſe ſome viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are preſented to their ph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>taſie, for they have dedicated ſome certain words to be ſaid in their minds motional, to be uſed when they would do any feats, beſides their faſting and prayer; and this thing they have dedicated to inquire of, is that which they divine with, or tell any thing from it, is much like unto the Aſtrologers, their Figure is dedicated for that purpoſe that he may tell things from and without the knowledge of the Figure, he can tell nothing except he were skilled in it before, but the Figure was the thing he came to know more then others at the firſt for wonderful things, may be accompliſhed through the ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination of reaſon when it hath ſet it ſelf apart, on purpoſe to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain unto ſuch things.</p>
               <p>For I finde by experience within this ſeventeen years, what ſtrange things hath bin atchieved by man and woman, who hath given themſelves up to an unknown God, upon a religions Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, ſome hath by their faſting and prayer unto an unknown God, attained unto viſions, appriſions, appearance of Angels, Voices, and many other ſtrange things; yet altogether ignorant of the true God and the right devil, and what Angels are; ſo that theſe things hath bin all within them; and they thought that God had revealed theſe things unto them; when as they did
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:98607:11"/>
attain unto theſe things aforeſaid by their own endeavors, as many Quakers and others can witneſs at this day, if they would; by hearkning to the light within them, and faſting, and ſuch like. Neither did God preſent any viſion, or ſpeak any voice unto them, but they do produce thoſe things aforeſaid by their own imaginations.</p>
               <p>So is it with Witches, they do raiſe ſhapes and voices out of themſelves, and thoſe voices they hear they are no other but mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional voices in themſelves, and the ignorant people that believes them is partakers of thoſe motional voices alſo with the Witch.</p>
               <p>For there is no ſpirit of the devil without them that doth aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume any ſhape or ſpeak any voice unro the Witch, neither doth any ſpirit without the Witch reveal any knowledge unto them, it is all produced by their own wicked imagination, who hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten within themſelves that familiar ſpirit they deal with, and not from any devil or ſpirit without them.</p>
               <p>But all cometh from the imagination within, that is, the devil and no other, yet this familiar ſpirit is produced from within them, to ſee ſhapes, and hear motional voices, meerly by watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the motion of the imagination that is placed in their minds or hearts, even as the Quakers do by hearkning to the light with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in them, they do procure many ſtrange viſions and motional voi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, but they being groundleſs and nonſenſical they come to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <p>LEt the Reader obſerve when King <hi>Saul</hi> asked the Witch of <hi>Endor, What forme the gods was of ſhe had ſeen aſcend out of the Earth;</hi> The Woman anſwered and ſaid, <hi>An old man with a
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:98607:12"/>
Mantle, &amp;c.</hi> But <hi>Saul</hi> ſaw nothing but as the Woman told him, and <hi>Saul</hi> believed her words, and bowed himſelf to the ground. —Now mind the 15. verſe, <hi>Samuel ſaid to Saul, why haſt thou diſquieted me to bring me up;</hi> the meaning is this, now the Witch had full power over <hi>Saul,</hi> ſo that he did really believe the Witch, that ſhe had indeed raiſed up <hi>Samuel,</hi> though he ſaw nothing — yet the fear of being deſtroyed by the Philiſtines, and the belief of the womans words, <hi>Samuel</hi> began to ſpeak in <hi>Sauls</hi> conſcience, that is, there came into <hi>Sauls</hi> minde the words that <hi>Samuel</hi> had told him in his life-time—. So that theſe was no ſpeaking to <hi>Saul</hi> by <hi>Samuel,</hi> but the reaſonings of <hi>Sauls</hi> own heart, and theſe voices that <hi>Samuel</hi> ſpake to <hi>Saul,</hi> they were motional voi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces that did ariſe in <hi>Sauls</hi> own heart—for an accuſing conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence will ſpeak dreadful voices in the Conſcience, as the blood of <hi>Abel</hi> cried for vengeance in <hi>Cain</hi>'s Conſcience, and the Saints that were ſlain under the Altar cried for vengeance, upon thoſe that ſhed their blood; ſo that a ſinful conſcience will have voices e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to torment him, though God himſelf, nor Prophet with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out him, doth never ſpeak unto him. A guilty Conſcience will ſpeak with a motional voice their great terrour and torment, which is greater then can be born, as it was with <hi>Cain, Saul,</hi> and <hi>Judas.</hi> Yea, ia was fear, and the remembrance of <hi>Sauls</hi> diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to <hi>Samuels</hi> words in his life-time, this did ariſe a freſh in <hi>Sauls</hi> mind, and ſpake with motional voices in <hi>Sauls</hi> conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, accuſing him for his diſobedience to <hi>Samuels</hi> words.</p>
               <p>For the remembrance of <hi>Samuels</hi> words may be ſaid to diſquiet <hi>Samuel,</hi> for <hi>Samuels</hi> words were buried in <hi>Sauls</hi> conſcience.</p>
               <p>But now, by his going to enquire of a Witch, <hi>Samuel</hi> is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vived again in <hi>Sauls</hi> mind, and there Samuel ſpeaks fear, wrath and terror; for <hi>Samuels</hi> words ſpake in <hi>Sauls</hi> conſcience one motional voice, and the guilt of <hi>Sauls</hi> diſobedience ſpake fear and horror in <hi>Sauls</hi> conſcience; this was a motional voice in <hi>Sauls</hi> conſcience alſo, for the voice of truth will ſpeak, or the voice of obedience, and the voice of ſin and diſobedience will ſpeak in mans Conſcience, as if they were two diſtinct ſpirits.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:98607:12"/>This many guilty Conſciences can witneſs, as we may reade by <hi>Cain</hi> that killed his brother, and <hi>Judas</hi> that betrayed his Lord, and many others who hath been guilty of the like crimes.</p>
               <p>So that the Witch did raiſe no <hi>Samuel,</hi> nor ſpirit, but a meer ſhadow it was the Witch ſaw which ſhe could raiſe by her Art; neither was there any <hi>Samuel</hi> or ſpirit not at all that did ſpeak to <hi>Saul,</hi> but that motional voice in <hi>Sauls</hi> Conſcience as aforeſaid.</p>
               <p>And in this ſence <hi>Samu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l</hi> may be ſaid to be diſquieted, for if <hi>Saul</hi> had never gone to the Witch to enquire of her, <hi>Samuels</hi> words had been quiet in <hi>Saul,</hi> neither would <hi>Saul</hi> have had ſuch reaſonings in himſelf, nor have been ſo ſenſible of the worm of his Conſcience.</p>
               <p>So that there was no voice of <hi>Samuel</hi> ſpake unto <hi>Saul</hi> but a motional voice in <hi>Sauls</hi> own minde or Conſcience, his fear and his diſobedience; and what <hi>Samuel</hi> had told him before theſe, all ſpeaking with voices in his wounded Conſcience; <hi>Samuels</hi> words ſpake one voice, and his own diſobedience ſpake another, ſo that the Witch of <hi>Endor</hi> did neither raiſe <hi>Samuel,</hi> but only made the King believe ſhe did, neither did <hi>Samuel</hi> ſpeak to the King but as aforeſaid.</p>
               <p>For the Kingdom being rent out of his hands, his ſons being deſtroyed, and all other threatnings of <hi>Samuel,</hi> they came into <hi>Sauls</hi> minde afreſh with ſtrong motions, ſo that they became as voices in <hi>Sauls</hi> heart, as if <hi>Samuel</hi> had ſpake to the hearing of the ear, for there was no <hi>Samuel</hi> raiſed nor no <hi>Samuel</hi> ſpake, but what was motional in the minde of <hi>Saul,</hi> and what did viſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally appear unto the Witch, which was a meer ſhadow which ſhe could produce by her Witchcraft-Art to all thoſe that were more ignorant then her ſelf, or had faith in her power.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:98607:13"/>
               <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
               <p>FOr the Reader muſt minde, that Witches and all thoſe that doth attain to the Viſions, and hear Voices within them, they do uſe means to attain unto it, alſo they have ſome ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Rule or Art, by which they come to enquire or to know things, that are above that knowledge which is common to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther people, it is much like unto the ways of God.</p>
               <p>Therefore let the Reader mind the ground-work laid down at the firſt, that the imagination of reaſon had begotten a ſon out of the Womb of the ſeed of reaſon in man, which I call the Mother and Imagination, the father and the ſon that is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten in the womb of reaſon; by imagination the father is that great wiſdom, knowledge and power, by which they go beyond other people who are of a lower capacity.</p>
               <p>This ſon is that familiar ſpirit Witches doth deal with; it is another ſpirit begotten in them, which was not in their birth, when they were born, but begotten in themſelves ſence by Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination as aforeſaid, neither is this familiar ſpirit produced, or doth come from any thing, or any devil without them, as people do vainly imagin; but the familiar ſpirit it is produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, and doth come from within, <hi>for out of the heart cometh evil thoughts, murder, adultery, &amp;c.</hi> and all familiar ſpirits, they are all conceived in the heart, and being conceived there, in its ſeaſon it bringeth forth ſuch ſpirits as are conceived in the heart; if envy and murder be conceived, as it was in <hi>Cain,</hi> then it bringeth forth the ſpirit or deed of murder; if luſt be conceived in the heart, it bringeth forth the ſpirit and act of adultery, as it did in <hi>David,</hi> and if a familiar ſpirit be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived in the heart, then it bringeth forth ſuch a ſpirit that ſhall ſpeak motional voices within them, as if ſome ſpirits without them did appear without a body, and ſpeak to them,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:98607:13"/>
and reveal thoſe things unto them.</p>
               <p>Many wicked ſpirits more then is mentioned, are conceived in the hearts of men and women, and acted by them ſpirits eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay, that were never of Gods Creation, but hath been conceived in the minde of man ſince; for when ſin is conceived, as in <hi>James</hi> 1.15. <hi>When luſt hath conceived it bringeth forth ſin, and ſin when it is finiſhed bringeth forth death;</hi> ſo that there is a conce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption of ſin firſt in the heart; and if it doth not die before it quickens into life, that is, into act; then it bringeth forth death, which is the puniſhment due to ſuch ſins, that are alive in mans actions, after they were conceived in the heart; and as the evil of murder, adultery and theft is conceived firſt in the heart, ſo is that familiar ſpirit witches and wizards have; they are firſt conceived in the mind, and in a little ſeaſon it groweth alive in them, and ſpeaketh unto them, as if it were without them; for this I ſay, that a familiar ſpirit is conceived and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten in the heart of man and wom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n as the other ſins afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned are, and the cauſe why God is more angry with thoſe that deal with a familiar ſpirit, and hath commanded them to be Put to death, more then for other ſins conceived in the mind is, becauſe they imitate the way of God, or the ſpirit of Propheſie, which cauſeth the people to believe in a meer fiction or ſhadow without any ſubſtance, that a ſpirit may be raiſed out of the ground without a body, and ſo they for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake the living God, who hath a body of his own, and gave life to every creature, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t hath a body and doth beleeve a lie, which hath been conceived in the mind, and hath quickned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a familiar ſpirit, and this ſpirit doth always live within the Witch, and not without her; and this familiar ſpirit thus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, firſt in the evil minde, and afterward quickning in the evil heart, it goeth from ſtrength to ſtrength, and from one de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of knowledge, to a further degree of evil knowledge, and evil wiſdom, as all things elſe doth that hath life, for ſin hath life in it, and the outward Law cauſeth ſin to revive in every one that doth evil, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.9. thus in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure the Reader may underſtand what a familiar ſpirit is, and how it comes to have a being in Witches and Wizards, and how the ignorant are partakers with the familiar ſpirit.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:98607:14"/>In the next place, I ſhall ſhew how thoſe that have a familiar ſpirit do imitate the way of God, or the way of true Prophets; obſerve the way and manner of true Prophets, High-Prieſts, and all other people, who are richly gifted with the ſpirit of Propheſie, or revelation for the ſeed of faith planted in the heart is the ſeed and nature of God, as reaſon is the ſeed and nature of the Serpent or devil, and as the ſeed of reaſon is the womb or mother for imagination to get a ſon.</p>
               <p>So likewiſe the ſeed of faith in man is the womb or mother for the revelation of faith, to beget a ſon out of the ſeed of ſaith, anſwerable as the Imagination doth out of the ſeed of reaſon.</p>
               <p>And this ſon the revelation hath begotten out of the ſeed of faith, is that heavenly wiſdome, diſcerning knowledge and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er over the ſpirits of others, and knowledge of things above the Stars, and knoweth the true God in forme and nature, with many other heavenly ſecrets, which none elſe can know but thoſe that believe them.</p>
               <p>So that the Revelation of faith hath begotten this heavenly wiſdom, power and glory out of the ſeed of faith, which is the ſeed of God, even of his divine nature, and this wiſdom, power and glory, is that ſon or ſpirit, by which all Prophets, High-Prieſts, Apoſtles and others that have it.</p>
               <p>I ſay this is that by which they can truly divine by, in that they can foretel truly what ſhall come to paſs, according to the knowledge of the revelation of faith, and this wiſdome and knowledge being produced by revelation out of the womb of the ſeed of faith, it may and is called the ſpirit of God in man, that doth teach and ſhew the wiſdom of God to others, ſo that others cometh to be taught and ſubjected by it, to their great peace here, and eternal Joy hereafter.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:98607:14"/>
               <head>CHAP. V.</head>
               <p>ANd this ſpirit of wiſdom, knowledge and power which is produced by the revelation as aforeſaid, it hath motional voices in the Conſcience, as the familiar ſpirit hath in the evil Conſcience, but the motional voices in a good conſcience ſpeaketh peace; likewiſe this motional voice in Prophets, High Prieſts, Apoſtles, and others, is that by which they do foretel things by, whether it be good or bad, that ſhall befal thoſe that ſhall enquire.</p>
               <p>Alſo the ſpirit of revelation hath a ſtanding rule to inquire by, as thoſe have that doth tell things by a familiar ſpirit, as I ſaid before, for the Witches doth imitate the way of Prophets, and the devils way is as like Gods way as he can.</p>
               <p>Now let the Reader minde, and he may ſee how men have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of the Lord by motional voices in the minde, by that ſpirit of faith which is gotten by revelation, which is called the Spirit of God.</p>
               <p>In the time of the Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> the Ephod was a ſtanding Rule, for to enquire of God for good or bad ſucceſs. Now there was no man could tell what the event would be that look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon the Ephod, but ſuch men as had the ſpirit of revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and propheſie in them, as <hi>David</hi> and the High Prieſt, aſſoon as ever they looked upon the Ephod, they could tell whether they ſhould proſper in battel or not; but if any other man which had not the ſpirit of revelation and propheſie ſhould look upon the Ephod, they could tell nothing by it.</p>
               <p>Though the Ephod was appointed of God, on purpoſe to enquire of God, yet none could find out Gods minde, but ſuch men aforeſaid, for as ſoon as ever <hi>David</hi> or the High Prieſt looked upon the Ephod, they could tell what the event would be, as may be ſeen, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23.6, 9. how <hi>David</hi> called for the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:98607:15"/>
Ephod, and <hi>Abiathar</hi> the Prieſt, to bring it to enquire of the Lord.</p>
               <p>Yet God never ſpake to them by voice, yet they had motio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal voices in themſelves in their hearts, aſſuring them that they proſper or not proſper, yet God never appeared himſelf, nor any Angel, neither did God ſpeak by any voice, yet they are bade to go &amp; proſper, as if they had heard ſom voice by looking upon the Ephod, ſo that thoſe voices that bade them go and proſper, they were motional voices that did ariſe from the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation and ſpirit of Propheſie within them by that skill they had in the Ephod, which was appointed of God for that purpoſe; ſo that all <hi>Davids</hi> voices, and the High Prieſts voices, that were motional voices, yet called the voice of God, becauſe they did ariſe from the ſeed of faith in <hi>David</hi> and others, which is the divine Nature of God, therefore called the Spirit of God.</p>
               <p>For this I ſay, if <hi>Saul</hi> had not loſt that ſpirit of Propheſie by his diſobedience, as he once had, when the good ſpirit depart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from him, he might have enquired of the Ephod, and have been anſwered with a motional voice by the Ephod, as he was by enquiring of a Witch.</p>
               <p>For the ſpirit of <hi>Samuel</hi> did ſpeak no more to <hi>Saul,</hi> then the Spirit of God did ſpeak to <hi>David,</hi> they were both motional voices that did ariſe from their two ſeeds, the one voice ſpake peace and deliverance, and the other ſpake wrath and deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, the one did enquire in the way that God did appoint, even of the Ephod, or of the Lords Prophets; the other did enquire of that which was forbidden, and forſook the Lord and his Prophets, and went to a Witch to enquire, it was becauſe one was the ſeed of <hi>Adam,</hi> which is the ſeed of God, and ſo choſen of God in mercy, even <hi>David;</hi> and the other was the ſeed of the Serpent, even the devil, who was choſen King in Gods wrath, even <hi>Saul.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is the true Interpretation of thoſe voices that <hi>Samuel</hi> ſpake to <hi>Saul,</hi> and of his being raiſed by the Witch of <hi>Endor.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore you that can underſtand theſe things aforementi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:98607:15"/>
you may ſee how the whole world lieth in darkneſs, and are cheated of their ſenſe and reaſon by this lying and vain ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination, to believe that ſpirits can be without bodies, or that ſpirits can be raiſed without bodies, or that ſpirits can ſpeak without bodies, or that ſpirits departed can aſſume any ſhapes afterwards, theſe things and many more are produced by the dark imagination of the heart of man; and if the Reader hath any true light of faith in him, he may underſtand the Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation I have given of the Witch of <hi>Endor,</hi> and how a familiar ſpirit is produced or begotten in them, and be ſatisfied in his mind as to that matter, ſo much concerning thoſe words in <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel</hi> aforementioned.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
               <p>AGain it is ſaid <hi>Iſa.</hi> 8.29. the Prophet ſpeaking there to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>believing Iſraelites that did not believe the Word of the Lord through the Prophets mouths concerning the deſtruction that ſhould come upon <hi>Iſrael;</hi> this judgement did the Lord threaten by the mouth of his Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> to bring upon <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> for their unbelief; and this Prophet ſeeing the people would not hearken unto the voice of the Lords Prophets, nor inquire of them, but altogether perſecuted them as falſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, deceivers and liers, and the inclination of their hearts was more willing and deſirous to enquire of a Witch or Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard, who had a familiar ſpirit then of the Prophet of the Lord, as you may ſee chap. and verſe abo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e-written, the words are theſe as followeth.</p>
               <p>And when they ſhall ſay unto you, ſeek unto them that have familiar ſpirits, and unto wizards that peep and that mutter, ſhould not a people ſeek unto their God for the living to the dead; the meaning of theſe words is this, that unbelieving men do think and believe that Witches and Wizards who hath
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:98607:16"/>
a familiar ſpirit can riſe out of the ground where dead men were buried, living ſpirits without bodies that can reveal things unto them, by that motional voice that doth proceed from theſe familiar ſpirits, which doth peep and mutter.</p>
               <p>That is the whiſperings that proceeds from this familiar ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, that is begotten by the imagination of reaſon the father, and the ſeed of reaſon the mother, as I ſaid before, is that motional voice all Witches and Wizards have, whereby they peep and mutter in themſelves, as if they did hear voices and ſee ſhapes, and living ſpirits ariſe out of the ground, as the Witch of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor</hi> ſaid to King <hi>Saul, She ſaw Gods aſcend out of the earth.</hi> Whenas there was no ſpirit nor ſhape came out of the ground at all, but the gods ſhe ſaw aſcend out of the earth came out of her own imagination, even that familiar ſpirit begotten in her, it ſeemed unto her as if it did aſcend out of the earth, but thoſe gods ſhe ſaid ſhe ſaw aſcend out of the earth, they aſcended out of her own imagination, and <hi>Saul</hi> beleeved her, and ſo was partakers with her, and he did believe that ſhe had raiſed <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muels</hi> ſpirit out of the earth, as the Witch had ſaid.</p>
               <p>And this is to be minded by the Reader, that when ſpirits are to be raiſed by Witches, her familiar ſpirit always ariſeth out of her own ſelf, even from the ſeed of reaſon and imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of her own heart, whereby ſhe doth hear voices within her, whiſpering low voices, as if ſome other ſpirits without her did ſpeak with a low voice unto her, and preſent ſhapes unto her dazled eyes, which ſeemeth to the Witch to be real voi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of a ſpirit without her, and a real ſhape without her, when as in deed and in truth, it ariſeth out of her own ſelf, even from the ſeed of reaſon, and imagination of her own heart, whereby ſhe doth hear voices within her whiſpering low voices, as if ſome other ſpirit without her did ſpeak with a low voice to her, and preſent ſhapes to her dazled eyes, which ſeemeth to the Witch to be a real voice of a ſpirit without her, and a real ſhape without her, when as in deed and in truth it is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but a motional voice begotten in her ſelf, and ſhapes begotten in her ſelf, by the imagination in the Womb of reaſon as aforeſaid, which is that familiar ſpirit.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:98607:16"/>Which is that familiar ſpirit ſhe doth deal with, ſhe thinking it is from ſome ſpirit without her, ſhe not knowing it is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten in her; and this familiar ſpirit begotten in her, it whiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers within her with a low motional voice, as if ſome ſpirit did whiſper out of the ground. According to that ſaying of the Prophet, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 28.4. concerning the deſtruction or Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God upon <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> the words are theſe, <hi>And thou ſhalt be brought down and ſhalt ſpeak out of the ground, and thy ſpeech ſhall be low out of the duſt, and thy voice ſhall be as one that hath a familiar ſpirit out of the ground, and thy ſpeech ſhall whiſper out of the duſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As if the Prophet ſhould ſay, Seeing you have refuſed to hearken to the voice of the Prophets, which hath declared the mind of the God of <hi>Iſrael</hi> openly with a loud voice; you have heard them ſpeak plain words with your ears, but you have not believed they ſpoke truth unto you: therefore you have re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ected the word of the Lord by his Prophets, and have perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted and ſlain ſome of them as falſe Prophets, becauſe they ſpake unto you in the Name of the Lord, as it was revealed by the ſpirit of revelation in them.</p>
               <p>They ſpake plain words unto you, as might be heard to the outward ear by the ſtanders by; they were viſible men that ſpake unto you, ſo that you need not to enquire after any that hath a familiar ſpirit, who ſpeaketh ſo ſoftly and ſo low, that no ſtanders by can hear this familiar ſpirit ſpeak, but he or ſhe that hath it.</p>
               <p>But as for plain words openly declared by the Prophets, and publickly heard by the outward ear, theſe you have rejected, deſpiſed, perſecuted, and counted them lyars, deceivers, falſe prophets, and ſuch like: Therefore God hath given you over to ſtrong deluſions, to enquire of a Witch, who makes you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that ſpirits may be raiſed out of the ground, and that ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits do come out of the duſt, and whiſper to the Witch with a low voice, that none can hear but her ſelf. So thoſe that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire do believe as King <hi>Saul</hi> did, that a familiar ſpirit can en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into the duſt or ground, and bring up another mans ſpirit that is dead without its body, and ſo their two ſpirits whiſper ſo low together, that none can hear that ſtands by, nor tell what
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:98607:17"/>
this ſpirit that is raiſed did ſay, nor whether the ſpirit ſo raiſed is gone into the body again, or into the ground from whence the Witch ſaid it was raiſed, which ſpirit that is ſaid to be rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, or ſaid to ſpeak out of the ground, I ſay it was raiſed out of the Witches own body, and no where elſe; and thoſe low voices and whiſperings were both within her, and not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out her.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VII.</head>
               <p>NOw how a man may be ſaid to be brought down, and ſhall ſpeak out of the ground, and their ſpeech ſhall below out of the duſt: The meaning is, when a particular man or woman, or a people or nation, be in the ſame diſtreſs and condition as King <hi>Saul</hi> was, that is in danger of loſing his Crown and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, his natural life, and not onely ſo, but his Soul, is torment<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the fear of eternal death; this maketh the heart of man to melt in him; it makes his ſpeech to grow weak and feeble, ſo that his ſpeech can hardly be heard; it is even as if a man did ſpeak out of death, or out of the ground.</p>
               <p>A man with the extremity of outward and inward trouble, he becomes ſpeechleſs, yet he ſpeaks in his thoughts, but ſo low, that none that ſtands by can hear or tell what he ſaith. This many can experience, that have ſeen their friend or relation in this condition; this is like ſpeaking out of the ground, and low out of the duſt. And the voice of every ſuch troubled ſoul, who hath the plagues of this life, and the horrour of conſcience as to the life to come, as King <hi>Saul</hi> had the voice ſuch people have, is as one that hath a familiar ſpirit out of the ground, and their ſpeech ſhall be as if one did whiſper out of the duſt.</p>
               <p>This place of Scripture hath the ſame meaning as the place before mentioned, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 8.19. where ſuch as King <hi>Saul</hi> was are
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:98607:17"/>
bade to ſeek unto them that have familiar ſpirits, and unto wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zards, that peep and mutter, (that is) that whiſper out of the ground; for whiſper, peep, and mutter, ſignifies all one thing.</p>
               <p>Theſe things did <hi>Manaſſeh,</hi> 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 21.6. he dealt with fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar ſpirits, and did great abominations; he made his ſons to paſs thorough the fire, in offering them up as a ſacrifice to an unknown Devil, which he thought was God, and this he did by the whiſperings of the familiar ſpirit within him, and being acquainted with others, who were known to have familiar ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits alſo. And ſo did ſeveral other Kings of <hi>Iſrael</hi> deal with fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar ſpirits, and had thoſe low whiſpering voices in themſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ves, as if ſpirits had riſen out of the ground, or from the duſt to ſpeak unto them; and this they did attain unto by induſtry, in that they forſook the words of the Prophets, and would not hearken unto them, but gave themſelves up to follow the ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations of their own hearts; imagining they might as well know God, and what worſhip would pleaſe God as well as the Prophets; therefore why ſhould we, being Kings, hearken to ſuch mean inferiour men as theſe? may not we by our familiar ſpirit as well know God, and what worſhip will pleaſe him by our familiar ſpirit, as the Prophets do by the ſpirit of prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy? why ſhould we be in ſuch bondage, that we can do nothing but what they ſay the Lord commands us to do? ſo the imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation ſaith; Come, we will not be tied up thus; we will ſee what our familiar ſpirit begotten in us will do; we will erect and build altars in ſeveral places, and ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>crifice bullocks and lambs to an unknown God; and ſo by this means they procure in themſelves low motional voices, which whiſper in themſelves, which becomes in them a familiar ſpirit, is produced in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: and there is a more increaſe of low motional voices, which doth whiſper in the mind, moving them to a further de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of knowledge and endeavour after more voices, ſo that to attain to this diabolical wiſdom in a more high meaſure. They are moved by this low voice within them to offer up their own children in ſacrifices to their imaginary God, which they believe is an inviſible ſpirit without a body, which reveals theſe things unto them, and whiſpers and ſpeaks thoſe voices unto them.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:98607:18"/>They count nothing too dear for this their imaginary God, no not their own ſons and daughters, as <hi>Manaſſeh</hi> and others did, that made their ſons and daughters paſs through the fire as a ſacrifice to their imaginary God, that had ſpake ſo many voices to them, and had whiſpered to them.</p>
               <p>But all theſe whiſperings and low voices, and peeping of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits out of the ground, as they thought, I ſay they were all within them; for when they came in any trouble, their famili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar ſpirit departs from them, and will not comfort them any more, let it be either in poor or rich, nay Kings that have dealt with familiar ſpirits, when they have been in trouble, all their comfort hath been loſt, as the pooreſt Witch that is, as may be ſeen by <hi>Manaſſeh</hi> and other Kings ſpoken of in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture.</p>
               <p>Now obſerve, when God doth bring upon a people, nation, or partitular perſon, ſome great judgment and deſtruction, let it be either outward or inward in the mind, when it comes up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a people, nation, or particular perſon, for their ſins and wickedneſs they have committed, in forſaking the Lords Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, and dealing with Witches and familiar ſpirits, as <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ul</hi> forſook the Lord and went to a Witch, and <hi>Manaſſeh,</hi> and ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral other Kings of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> who ought onely to have obeyed the Prophets of the Lord; but they forſook him, and enquired of Witches and Wizards, and dealt with familiar ſpirits them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and cauſed the people to worſhip the Devil (whom they imagined to be God) inſtead of the true God, whom the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets would have had them to worſhip.</p>
               <p>But when this puniſhment for ſin is inflicted upon a people, nation, or particular perſon, for dealing with familiar ſpirits, and worſhipping of devils; when puniſhment comes, it makes the heart or hearts to fail, for the ſpirit is brought down by this judgment even to death, and ſo goeth to the ground; ſo that the very fear, trouble, and ſorrow of heart, ſhall ſpeak as it were out of the duſt, or out of death; for ſin will ſpeak out of the ground, and the ſpeech of death will below in them that
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:98607:18"/>
have eſcaped the deſtruction which others did go through; for there will be a reſemblance in thoſe that have eſcaped how their friends and relations are fallen to the ground or duſt of the earth for their wickedneſs, ſo that ſorrow and grief will ſpeak in the mind of thoſe that have eſcaped with a low ſpeech, even as one doth who hath a familiar ſpirit. Or as if their friends and relations, the remembrance of their deſtruction being taken away in wrath for ſin, it ſpeaks a ſmall low voice of grief and ſorrow in the heart of thoſe that are alive, even as one th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t hath a familiar ſpirit, even a low motional voice of ſorrow and grief, and it cometh as it were out of the ground, or out of the duſt.</p>
               <p>That is the very influence of grief and ſorrow, for their dead friends and people; it cauſeth, where grief is, to hear as it were low voices and ſmall ſpeeches, even out of the ground or out duſt of the earth: juſt as it was with <hi>Cain</hi> in another caſe, the Lord ſaid to <hi>Cain, Thy brothers bloud crieth from the ground for vengeance;</hi> and ſo the bloud of thoſe that were ſl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n under the altar did <hi>from the ground cry for vengeance,</hi> as in <hi>Rev.</hi> 6.10. it crieth for vengeance in the conſciences of all bloudy perſecutors. So in like manner doth the death and deſtruction of a people, who are deſtroyed for wicked idolatry, as thoſe were the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſpeaketh of, they ſpake from the ground a low ſpeech in the conſcience of thoſe that were concerned, grief, ſorrow, and fear of the ſame puniſhment, and ſuch like.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:98607:19"/>
               <head>CHAP. VIII.</head>
               <p>FOr where grief and ſorrow is rooted and ſettled in the heart, it ſpeaketh with low motional voices in the mind, that is the thought of fear in the mind, both of temporal loſſes and the loſs of eternal peace. The fear moves to and fro in that mind, as if it were a ſpeech out of the ground: for the thoughts of the heart are low voices which cannot be heard by any but them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
               <p>So is it with thoſe that have a familiar ſpirit, their voices and ſpeech they hear from ſpirits without them, as if ſpirits did ſpeak to them out of the ground: which ſpeech they ſay they hear, is nothing elſe but the thoughts that paſs to and fro in their own minds, a low motional voice in themſelves, as if ſpirits did ſpeak to them with a low voice out of the ground, or out of the duſt. For their faith is ſtrong, and above all thoſe that come to enquire of a Witch, they do all believe that ſpirits may be raiſed without bodies out of the ground; as the Witch doth, ſo they both do believe, that the ſpirit come out of the ground that ſpake thoſe low voices to the Witch, and ſhe tells it to the other that enquire of her, and they believe her as King <hi>Saul</hi> did.</p>
               <p>So they are wholly departed from the Lord, and believe a lie, to think that ſpirits can be raiſed out of the ground with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out bodies after men have been dead; it is a thing God never did; we never read in Scripture, that God or his Prophets did ever raiſe any ſpirits out of the ground without bodies after they were dead; but we read in Scripture, that God and his Prophets have raiſed ſome from the dead with bodies, as that of <hi>Lazarus</hi> being raiſed out of the ground by Chriſt, and the Child that was raiſed from death by the Prophet <hi>Elijah,</hi> and another Child raiſed from death to life by the Prophet <hi>Eliſha,</hi> and ſeveral others come forth out of the ground at the riſing
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:98607:19"/>
again of Chriſt from death, as thoſe Saints that did ariſe out of the graves, and appeared to many that were alive; theſe all did ariſe out of the graves with bodies after they were dead, and <hi>Lazarus</hi> came forth out of the ground after he was dead, but his ſpirit came not out of the ground without his body, but bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and ſoul came out of the ground together.</p>
               <p>For it was always Gods practice to raiſe ſoul and body toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and becauſe the imagination of reaſon in thoſe that have a familiar ſpirit cannot do ſo, nor thoſe that enquire of them, therefore they do imagine that ſpirits may be raiſed out of the ground without bodies, or aſſume a ſhape and appear like a bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, yet it ſhall be of no ſubſtance, a ſhape that can neither be felt nor handled by the hand of man.</p>
               <p>Now mind, all thoſe God doth raiſe out of the ground after they were de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d, they may be handled and felt; though they be ſpiritual bodies, yet they may be felt and handled, as Chriſt ſaid to <hi>Thomas, Feel me and handle m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> after he was riſen from the dead, and <hi>Thomas laid his fingers in the print of the nails, and on his ſide.</hi> Yet Chriſt was at that time a ſpiritual body that was riſen from the dead, that might be felt and handled, and not a ſpirit without a body, as moſt people do vainly imagine that ſpirits may be raiſed without bodies.</p>
               <p>And as for that <hi>Lazarus</hi> and others, that were raiſed by the power of God out of the ground after they had been dead, they had bodies as well as ſpirits that might be ſeen with natu al eyes, and handled and felt with natural hand. So that Gods power in raiſing the dead, it is no cheat; the creature is not cheated nor deceived, but is fully ſatisfied in his mind.</p>
               <p>But for a familiar ſpirit to ſay or tell people, they de or can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taiſe ſpirits out of the ground in ſuch a ſhape without a body or bodily ſubſtance; or ſhall ſay they hear voices from this ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit ſo raiſed, is a mere cheat to the ignorant and unbelieving, and le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ds them into the pit of darkneſs, and makes them fear where no fear is, and are afraid of their own ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dows; for it is the n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ure of reaſon the devil to imagine, that this way of raiſing of ſpirits without bodies, to be of a more high nature
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:98607:20"/>
then to raiſe ſpirit and body together, as God doth; and the imagination doth conceive it a more great power to raiſe ſpirits without bodies out of the duſt of the ground, then it is to r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſe ſpirit and body together, as Chriſt did; for Chriſt always raiſed ſpi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>it and body together, as the Scriptures do teſtifie.</p>
               <p>For the reaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n in man doth ſend forth the imagination of the heart, the unclean ſpirit in man walking through dry places, ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>king <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſt but can find none; the ignorant dark thoughts of the im<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gination goeth out of a man, to enquire of one that hath a familiar ſpirit, ſeeking reſt but can find none, as King <hi>Saul</hi> did: for the imagination of the heart being continually evil, it always walketh through dry places, where no matter of life is to be had, to quench the thirſt of ſin or a defiled conſcience; nei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>her can the th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ughts of imagination be ſatisfied with what a Witch or a Familiar ſaith; therefore called dry places: they may be called dry, becauſe the heart is never ſatisfied with what a Witch ſaith, for ſhe always ſaith a lie.</p>
               <p>To tell a man or woman, that ſhe doth or can raiſe ſpirits out of the ground without bodies, as the Witch of <hi>Endor</hi> did to King <hi>Saul,</hi> or that ſhe did hear any low voice or ſpeech of <hi>Samuel</hi> out of the ground, as ſhe told the King; I ſay, ſhe did but cheat the King, and made him believe ſhe had raiſed <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel,</hi> and had heard him ſpeak to her with a low ſpeech out of the ground, which had revealed unto her what ſad things would befall the King: ſo he believing her words, his ſpirit fainted, ſo that no ſtrength was in him; when as indeed and in truth that <hi>Samuel</hi> ſhe ſaid ſhe ſaw ariſe out of the earth, he did ariſe out of her own heart; and that low ſpeech ſhe ſaid <hi>Samuel</hi> ſpake, it was all in her ſelf by the motions of the familiar ſpirit begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in her. And King <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ul</hi> believing her, being partaker of her faith, <hi>Samuel</hi> ſpake a low motional voice or ſpeech in him alſo, he believing it was <hi>Samuel</hi> ſpake out of the earth, but it was nothing elſe but the voice of his own guilty conſcience within himſelf, as it was the voice her familiar ſpirit in her ſelf that ſpake as aforeſaid.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:98607:20"/>So that the meaning of the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> chap. 29.4. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the deſtruction of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> that <hi>grief and ſorrow of heart ſhould ſpeak in themſelves;</hi> as if the ſpeech came out of the ground, becauſe they ſaw in themſelves nothing but death and deſtruction did approch, and was like to follow upon them all, fearing they ſhould all be deſtroyed by their enemies, and ſlain and fall to the ground: ſo that fear of heave of deſtruction, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſpake a low ſpeech in every mans heart, even as if it ſpake out of the ground, or as one that hath a familiar ſpirit; for it is the nature of a familiar ſpirit to ſpeak as if the ſpeech did pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from the earth, and the ſpeech doth ſeem to the Witch, and thoſe that enquire of her, to whiſper out of the duſt: whenas the ſpeech cometh not out of the ground, neither doth it whiſper out of the duſt, as is imagined by moſt people, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ignorance and darkneſs hath overſpread the minds of moſt people in the world. But that low ſpeech the familiar ſpirit ſpe ks or whiſpers, it is out of her own heart, even that wiſdom begotten by the imagination in her own thoughts, that ſpeaks as aforeſaid, and no ſpirit without her, as hath vainly been ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined.</p>
               <p>So likewiſe the people of the <hi>Jews,</hi> the fear, grief, and ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row of heart, being begotten in them for ſuch like lins, as that of witchcraft, idolatry, dealing with familiar ſpirits, cauſing their ſons and daughters to paſs through the fire as burnt offerings and ſacrifices unto Devils, which they ſuppoſed to be Gods; theſe things cauſed their hearts to fail and faint, and their thoughts were troubled within themſelves, which cauſeth their ſpeech to grow weak and low within them, even as if ſome fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar did ſpeak out of the ground, or whiſper out of the duſt, fear, grief, and ſorrow of heart: but all come out of their own grieved hearts, who were puniſhed for their ſins; and not out of the natural ground or natural duſt, as people do vainly ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine. This is the true meaning of the Prophets words, and how familiar ſpirits may be ſaid to ſpeak out of the ground, and whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſper out of the duſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:98607:21"/>
               <head>CHAP. IX.</head>
               <p>AGain, it hath been objected by many, that ſpirits may be raiſed without bodies, and that ſpirits may be talked with after they have been dead and buried; and that ſpirits have ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared in a ſhape to ſeveral people, yet this ſpirit ſo appearing hath no body nor ſubſtance at all, neither can it be felt or hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by mortal man, nor no immortal creature neither: this is the vain conceit of moſt people.</p>
               <p>But to ſatisfie the Reader in this, I declare, that there is no immortal ſpirit whatſoever, but it hath a ſpiritual body ſutable to its ſpirit; if the ſpirit be immortal, the body is immortal alſo: for this I ſay, no ſpirit can have any being at all without a body, no not God himſelf, who was from eternity; his ſpirit could not be from eternity without a ſpiritual body, in form like a man; they were both from eternity, and the one was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver divided nor ſeparated from the other, but they were both eternal. And further I declare, that God was a ſpiritual body from eternity, in form like a Man; therefore God created man in his own image and likeneſs. Now obſerve, if man hath a body ſutable to his ſpirit, ſo hath God a body ſutable to his ſpirit; elſe man was not created in his image, if God hath ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver a body, but is all ſpirit, as people do vainly imagine. For this I know, that God was ſpirit and body, in form like a Man, from eternity, and his ſpirit was never divided nor ſeparated from his body, but they were both eternal.</p>
               <p>So likewiſe is it with Angels and Men, and all other crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; whereever the ſpirit of life is, there is bodies of life al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo; let it be either in ſpiritual bodies, or in natural bodies. For if the body of either of theſe be dead, the ſpirit is dead alſo; and if the ſpirit be dead either in ſpiritual body or natural bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, the body is dead alſo: for the one cannot have any ſenſible
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:98607:21"/>
being without the other. And further I ſay, that they we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e both together ſpirit and body from eternity in God the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, and he hath ordered and created all his creatures, both celeſtial and terreſtrial, that ſpirit and body ſhould be one li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving being, and that one ſhould not ſubſiſt nor have no ſenſible being without the other: even as God himſelf could not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy no ſenſible living being without a body, he knowing this in himſelf.</p>
               <p>Therefore he created all his creatures ſpiritual and natural with bodies ſutable to their ſpirits, and ſpirits ſutable to their bodies, ſo that one might not be divided nor ſeparated from the other; for if one dieth, the other dieth; and if the ſpirit live, the body liveth alſo. For this I ſay, that if the ſpirit of God himſelf could not be without a body from eternity, how then is it poſſible that his creatures ſhould have ſpirits without bodies, ſeeing he himſelf his ſpirit could not have any being without his body from eternity.</p>
               <p>But this conceit, that the ſpirit or ſoul of man is immortal, and cannot die, and may have a being without a body, and appear in a ſhape without any ſubſtance; this vain conceit proceeded firſt from the imagination of reaſon in man, even from <hi>Cain,</hi> the firſt devil in fleſh and bone. And this imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in <hi>Cain</hi> his poſterity, being heathen men, who had no communion with God, nor revelation of faith, as the ſons of <hi>Adam</hi> and the ſons of <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>h,</hi> the generation of the righteous, had; they knew that the ſpirit and body was all one ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance.</p>
               <p>But the imagination of reaſon, <hi>Cain</hi> his poherity, the heathen opinion do imagine the ſpirit of man to be immortal, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not dies; and that ſpirits may appear in ſhapes without bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies; and that ſpirits may go out of the body, and go to heaven or hell and leave the body to be laid in the ground, as the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers and others do.</p>
               <p>And this imagination of reaſon in man hath created to it ſelf a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> creation, which God never created. Man hath created
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:98607:22"/>
and made in his imagination a ſpirit without a body, and that this ſpirit ſo created is immortal, and cannot die, nor is not capable of death, that it can ſlip out of the body, and that it can have a being when it is gone out of the body, and appear in a ſhape without ſubſtance, or hath power to aſſume what ſhape it pleaſe, and yet this ſhape it doth aſſume ſhall have no ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, yet it ſhall appear in a ſhape and fright people.</p>
               <p>And the imagination of reaſon in man hath created man in his own image and likeneſs, as God did <hi>Adam:</hi> as thus, Firſt, he hath conceived in his imaginat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on, that God is a ſpirit with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a body. Secondly, he conceiveth in his imagination that the Devil is a ſpirit flying in the air, which can neither be ſeen nor felt; yet this Devil or ſpirit without a body doth tempt man to evil, whereby man is puniſhed, and the tempter he is eſcaped away without puniſhment.</p>
               <p>Alſo it is conceived by the imagination, that this Devil or ſpirit is in hell fire, and in chains of darkneſs, and can go no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then God will permit him, becauſe his chain is no longer then God hath limited him.</p>
               <p>Alſo it is conceived in the imagination, notwithſtanding the Devil is chained, and in hell fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e tormented, yet he being a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit without a body, he is ſo ſwift that he can be in all places at one time, ſo that he can tempt tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſands of men and women to ſin at one and the ſame time, and they themſelves never the wiſer, nor know him when he tempted them. All this the imaginary Devil can do, and much more; and yet be in hell fire, and tied in a chain at the ſame time, and all but one Devil, a ſpirit without a body.</p>
               <p>Alſo the the imagination hath conceived that the ſoul of man is a ſpirit infuſed or put into the body by God himſelf, and that man begets the body, but not the ſoul or life of man, that is conceived to be immortal, or a ſpirit that is ſo inviſible, that cannot be ſeen nor known what it is, and that it can live of it ſelf when it is gone out of the body.</p>
               <p>Thus the imagination of reaſon the devil hath created its own ſoul in its own image and likeneſs; and this hath been
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:98607:22"/>
the occaſion of producing of familiar ſpirits, and of dealing with thoſe that have a familiar ſpirit, being conformed to the very image of the devil. Many things more of the like nature might be ſaid in this point.</p>
               <p>But here the Reader may ſee if there be any true light of faith in him, how the imagination of reaſon in man hath crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſpirits without bodies, and that the Devil is a bodyleſs ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and in hell fire, and in a chain of darkneſs, and yet at liberty at the ſame time to tempt people, and in hell fire, and yet out of the fire when he pleaſeth, and that he may be c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed out of hell, or out of the ground, when a Witch by her familiar ſpirit doth call; and that he ſhall appear in any ſhape they wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l have him, yet he ſhall have no body nor ſubſtance, but a mere ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow; yet this ſhadow ſhall ſpeak with a low voice or ſpeech out of the ground; as if ſpeech could proceed from a ſhadow without ſubſtance.</p>
               <p>So that the imagination of the heart of man hath created to it ſelf a devil, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t God never created; and the imagination of mans heart hath created his own ſoul in the image and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the devil, that is to ſay, a ſpirit without a body; and that a ſpirit without a body may be capable of joy or ſorrow; and that a ſpirit may ſubſiſt and have a being injoy or ſorrow with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a body, which thing is impoſſible.</p>
               <p>But obſerve the creation that the imagination of man hath created to himſelf; for it is the nature of imagination of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon the devil, he always creates ſpirits without bodies, but God the Creator he always creates ſpirits and bodies together, for God never created any ſpirit without a body; for when God made man after his own image and likeneſs, he made him with a body as wel as a pirit, elſe man could not be made in the image and likeneſs of God, if God had not had a body of his own as well as a ſpirit.</p>
               <p>So that <hi>Adam</hi> was made or created in the image and likeneſs of God; for <hi>Adam</hi> had a viſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>le body and ſpirit, undivided and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:98607:23"/>
unſeparable one from the other; they were but one viſible ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible being, and when the life was dead the body was dead, and when the body is really dead, the ſpirit and life was and is dead alſo; and both are laid in the ground together, as is declared in all our writings, but more eſpecially in that book entituled <hi>The M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rtality of the Soul.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. X.</head>
               <p>ALſo I do further declare, that God did never create any ſpirit without a body, neither of Angels, nor Men, nor no other creature, neither in Heaven above, nor in the Earth beneath, nor in the Waters under the earth. There is no ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit or life whatſoever that is created of God, but it hath a body to that life or ſpirit; but if a ſpirit have any being with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a body, that ſpirit is none of Gods creation, for God never created any ſpirit whatſoever without a body, as I ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
               <p>But the imagination of reaſon in man, which is the devil, hath created all creatures in the imagination to have ſpirits without bodies, both of Angels above and Man here on earth, and all creatures upon the earth, and in the waters, that have the breath of life, the imagination of reaſon ſaith, their ſpirits may ſubſiſt without bodies, or go out of thoſe bodies they have, and enter into other bodies, and appear in the ſhape of a body, and yet be of no ſubſtance: ſo that the Devils creation is all of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits without bodies, and Gods creation is all with bodies and ſpirits together.</p>
               <p>And this darkneſs hath overſpread the nature of man all the world over, which is the occaſion of that opinion of houſes and places being hanted with evil ſpirits, and ſpirits walking with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out bodies, and dea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing with famili<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r ſpirits, that peep, and mutter, and whiſper as it were out of the ground. Theſe things
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:98607:23"/>
and many more are produced by the imagination of the heart of man, for the imagination of mans heart is evil, and continually evil; for it hath given a being to ſpirits without bodies, to fright it ſelf to that which hath no being of it ſelf.</p>
               <p>For I declare and perfectly know, that there is no ſuch thing as ſpirits to walk without bodies, nor aſſume any ſhape after death, nor be raiſed out of the ground by any Witch or any fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar ſpirit whatſoever; it is all produced out of the d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rk ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination of the heart, where ignorance beareh rule; for there is no ſuch thing can be preſented but to the ignorant and dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minded people.</p>
               <p>Thus I have given the Reader to underſtand ſomething more concerning the power of Witches, and how they may be ſaid to raiſe ſpirits out of the ground, and from whence that low ſpeech doth come, with thoſe Scriptures opened that ſpeak as if a familiar ſpirit did hear whiſpering out of the duſt.</p>
               <p>Alſo I have given the interpretation of that in <hi>Samuel</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Witch of <hi>Endor,</hi> and thoſe places of Scripture in <hi>Iſaiah;</hi> theſe places are the moſt concerning ſpirits being rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed without bodies, of any in the Scriptures; but there have been ſome other places of Scripture, that do ſeem to carry a ſhew as if ſpirits might riſe again without bodies, and I have been deſired by ſome to open thoſe Scriptures that ſeem to tend to that purpoſe, though the common and general objection amongſt all people is, that of the Witch of <hi>Endor</hi> and King <hi>Saul,</hi> which I have opened before; yet for the further ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the Reader, <hi>I</hi> ſhall open and interpret the other places objected, that ſeem to tend to the ſame thing.</p>
               <p>The places of Scripture are three; the firſt is <hi>Iſa.</hi> 61 1. the word<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> are theſe, <hi>The Spirit of the Lord God is upon me, becauſe the Lord hath anointed me to preach good tidings unto the meek: he hath ſent me to bind up the broken-hearted, to proclaim liberty to the captives, and the opening of the priſon to them that are bound</hi> — So <hi>Luke</hi> 4.88. the words in <hi>Luke</hi> are much to the ſame purpoſe, and little difference; onele that which <hi>Iſaiah</hi> did propheſie of, it was fulfilled by Chriſt in his time — So
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:98607:24"/>
the firſt Epiſtle of <hi>Peter,</hi> chap. 3. and 18, 19, 20. verſes; the words are theſe, <hi>For Chriſt alſo hath once ſuffered for ſin, the juſt for the unjuſt; that he might bring us to God, being put to death in the fleſh, but quickened by the Spirit.</hi> Verſe 19. <hi>By which alſo he went and preached unto the ſpirits in priſon:</hi> Verſe 20. <hi>Which ſometime were diſobedient, when once the long-ſuffering of God waited in the days of Noah, while the ark was a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>in few (that is) eight ſouls were ſaved by water.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XI.</head>
               <p>AS for th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t ſaying of the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> it was a prophecy of Chriſt, that he ſhould be anointed to preach glad ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings unto the meek, and that he was ſent to bind up the bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken-hearted, to proclaim liberty to the captives, and the open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the priſon to them that are bound. This prophecy was fulfilled when he was upon earth, as may plainly appear by thoſe words in <hi>Luke</hi> aforementioned.</p>
               <p>Alſo the Reader may underſtand, that theſe places of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture have no relation at all to the raiſing of ſpirits without bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies nor of ſpirits being in priſon, nor delivered out of priſon by the power of Chriſt without bodies.</p>
               <p>But the meaning is this, that the Spirit of the Lord Almighty was upon Chriſt, and in him, and did anoint him to preach glad tidings of ſalvation to the meek in heart, who did believe in him, and truſted in his words; all ſuch as were broken-heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, who were led captive by the error, ignorance, and darkneſs of the mind; he came to proclaim liberty to the ſpirit of man, who was in captivity; and to open the priſon door of mens hearts.</p>
               <p>For this I ſay, all mens ſpirits by nature are ſhut up in the priſon of ſpiritual darkneſs in the mind, and are lead captive by the ignorance of truth; ſo that the ſpirit or ſoul of man is
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:98607:24"/>
ſhut up priſoner in the body of man, untill the true God and Saviour hath been preached to them, as it was by Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, when on earth he was anointed to preach glad tidings of ſalvation; and he anointed his Apoſtles to preach glad tidings of peace to men, and to open the priſon, and to deliver the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptive out of captivity, and to ſet the ſpirits of many that were in a priſon of darkneſs in their own minds go free: this prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy was fulfilled at that time by Chriſt and his Apoſtles in their Commiſſion.</p>
               <p>But the ſame captivity and priſon of darkneſs is now upon the ſpirits of all men, as it was at that time: for this I ſay, and many people can witneſs that their ſpirits have been ſhut up priſoners in ſpiritual darkneſs in their own bodies, untill the the true God and Saviour hath been preached unto them by his laſt meſſengers.</p>
               <p>For this I declare, that thoſe words of the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> they were ſpoken with relation to a ſpiritual liberty, and to a ſpiritual captivity, of the mind or ſpirit of man, and not to a natural captivity. Neither was it meant the opening of the natural priſon doors, to them that were bound by the Powers of the nations; but the doors of mens hearts were opened at the preaching of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, in that light, and life, and ſalvation was preached unto them, that whoever believed that this Jeſus is the Chriſt, the Saviour of the world, ſhould be ſaved and delivered from the fear of eternal death: ſo that the ſoul of man that was lead captive into priſon, and bound in chains of darkneſs, and ſtrong doors lockt faſt to keep the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of man in priſon, by the works of the Law, and the expound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the Law before Chriſt came, the ſpirit of reaſon in them did lead the generality of people their ſpirits into ſpiritual ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptivity, and ſhut them up in priſon, and tied their ſpirits up in the obſervation of the Ceremonial Law of <hi>Moſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Which was as chains of darkneſs; and not onely ſo, but ſhut the door of hope upon them, ſo that there was no hope to be ſaved in them, but by obſerving the Law aforeſaid, which <hi>Paul</hi> calls <hi>beggerly rudiments, Gal.</hi> 3. So that this ſpiritual captivity,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:98607:25"/>
and being bound in priſon, and the doors being ſhut, it was the ſpirits of people that were captives and priſoners in their own bodies, kept by the Legal and ceremonial righteouſneſs of the Law of <hi>Moſes;</hi> and when Chriſt came to preach, and to give power to his Apoſtles to preach the Goſpel of truth, both to Jew and Gentile, then was the dore of hope opened in peoples hearts, and many that were bound in priſon, whoſe ſpirits were led captive, they were ſet at liberty from that bondage of the Ceremonial Law, wherein they were bound, and brought out of that priſon of darkneſs in the mind, into the glorious light and life of faith, by the preaching of Chriſt and his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles.</p>
               <p>Then was this prophecy of <hi>Iſaiah</hi> fulfilled in the Apoſtles commiſſion; then was liberty preached to the ſpirits of many that were bound and in priſon in their own minds, the word of faith preached unto them, it opened a door of hope of deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance from the bondage of the Law as aforeſaid, wherewith they were bound; ſo that by faith they had in Chriſt their chains fell off their feet, and darkneſs of their underſtanding; ſo that they were at perfect liberty, and delivered out of pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and the priſon door of hope in Chriſt being opened, all true believers in Chriſt were ſet at liberty, free from captivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and out of that ſpiritual priſon of darkneſs into the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious liberty of the ſons and daughters of God for ever and ever.</p>
               <p>So is it now in this commiſſion of the ſpirit, we the witneſſes of the ſpirit have preached glad tidings of ſalvation, and have opened the priſon doors of mens hearts, and have let many out of that ſpiritual priſon, that were bound to the righteouſneſs ſet up by the imagination of reaſon now in theſe laſt days, who were led captive by their own traditions, and kept in priſon in their own bodies for many years; but by the declaration of truth in all our writings and our ſpeakings, many people have been delivered out of captivity and out of priſon, their ſpirits have been let looſe out of the chains of darkneſs, becauſe the door of their hearts hath been opened by the word of faith in the true God, which we have preached and written; this
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:98607:25"/>
many can witneſs at this day the truth of it. So that now that Scripture is fulfilled again in theſe laſt days; and this is the true meaning of the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> in thoſe words concerning opening the priſon, and giving liberty to the captives that were impriſoned in their own bodies by the conceptions of the ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations of their own hearts.</p>
               <p>So that there is not the leaſt colour or ground from thoſe words, for the reaſon of man to think that ſpirits may be let out of priſon without bodies, or that the ſpirit of Chriſt did preach to any ſpirit in priſon without his body.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XII.</head>
               <p>ANd as for thoſe words of <hi>Peter</hi> aforenamed, where he ſaith, <hi>Chriſt was put to death in the fleſh, but quickened by the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; by which alſo he went and preached unto the ſpirits in priſon, which ſometime were diſobedient, when once the long-ſuffering of God waited in the days of Noah, while the ark was a prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The meaning of thoſe words are as followeth; that Chriſt was put to death in the body of his own fleſh, this is confeſſed by moſt people that profeſs the Scriptures of truth, but very few do truly believe, that the ſoul or ſpirit of Chriſt did die, or was put to death at all, notwithſtanding the Scripture ſaith, that <hi>He poured out his ſoul unto death;</hi> and he himſelf ſaith, <hi>His ſoul was heavy unto death.</hi> Therefore that the Reader may un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand what is meant in that Chriſt was put to death in the fleſh, but quickened by the ſpirit; mind,</p>
               <p>I declare, that it was the ſoul or ſpirit of Chriſt, which was the Godhead life that dwelt in that body of fleſh and bone of Chriſt; for as the Scripture ſaith, <hi>In him all the fulneſs of the Godhead dwelt bodily:</hi> and this Godhead life that dwelt in
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:98607:26"/>
the body of Chriſts fleſh, it was put to death in the body of Chriſts fleſh, and the ſame Godhead life that was put to death in the body of his fleſh: and when Chriſts body was crucified upon the croſs, then was the ſoul and life of Chriſt, or the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head life did die, and was put to death in that fleſh of Chriſt; for that fleſh of Chriſt was God become fleſh, as the Scripture ſaith; and the ſoul and life of Chriſt was the ſoul and life of God. And,</p>
               <p>When Chriſt poured out his ſoul unto death, it was the Godhead life that was poured out unto death; ſo that the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>he d ſpirit was put to death, and did die in the fleſh of Chriſt when he was crucified. But this Godhead life which was put to death in the fleſh of Chriſt, it quickened again where it was put to death, even in the ſame fleſh where it was put to death. And in its quickening ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>in, it raiſed the ſame fleſh again, and ſo ſpiritualized the ſame fleſh that ſuffered, and made it unca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable to ſuffer death any more.</p>
               <p>For this I ſay, no ſpirit or life that is put to death whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, could poſſibly quicken again in the ſame body, but the life of God onely; ſo that Chriſt muſt needs be God as well as Man, for it was Chriſt that was put to death in the fleſh, and the ſame life that was put to death, and did die, that which did die did quicken again, and ſo is called a quickening ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.</p>
               <p>Now obſerve, it cannot properly be called a quickening ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, if it had not been once dead: for if the ſpirit and life of Chriſt did not die, nor was not dead, then I ſay there was no need that this ſpirit and life ſhould quicken again, for it was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways quick and alive.</p>
               <p>For the ſpirit quickening doth imply, a ſenſible life is quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned out of an inſenſible life; as a child in the womb before it is quick, it feeleth no pain, neither doth it ſtir in the womb, and the midwife doth not care to deſtroy it to ſave the womans life, becauſe the child was not quick it was an inſenſible life, no more capable of pain then there is in death, or a dead lump of
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:98607:26"/>
earth; but when a child is quick in the womb, it is capable of pain, though it hath not ſtrength to expreſs it to us that are ſtrong, yet it is capable of pain, becauſe it is quickened into a ſenſible life, that is, a living ſoul, a living ſpirit, and ſo may be called a quickened ſpirit of life, out of that which was dead; yet by the appointment of God in his creation, and the warm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the womb, there is a new life or ſpirit doth quicken in the womb in its ſeaſon, according to the appointment of God, when he created all things, and placed a law of generation in them.</p>
               <p>So likewiſe the ſpirit or life of Chriſt was put to death in his own body of fleſh, as aforeſaid; and in its ſeaſon he himſelf had appointed before, namely three days and three nights, this ſpirit of Chriſt ſo put to death, it quickened again in the ſame fleſh a new and glorious life, which made that fleſh that ſuffered glorious alſo.</p>
               <p>And this is the true interpretation of <hi>Peters</hi> words, and the faith of all true believers, that the ſpirit, life, and ſoul of Chriſt did die, and was put to death in the body of his own fleſh, that was crucified on the croſs by the Jews; and that the ſame ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit that was put to death, it did quicken again out of death in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a new and glorious life by his own power, therefore called a quickening ſpirit.</p>
               <p>So that here is no ground at all for that vain conceit in peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, who do believe that ſpirits may be raiſed without bodies, or appear without bodies, but altogether to the contrary. And as for that ſaying of <hi>Peter, By which alſo he went and preached unto the ſpirits in priſon, which ſometime were diſobedient, when once the long-ſuffering of God waited in the days of Noah while the ark was a preparing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe words do ſeem to carry ſome ſhew, as if the quickening ſpirit of Chriſt, after he was riſen from the dead or in the time he did lie in the grave, as if his ſpirit in that interim of time went into ſome local place where ſpirits were in priſon with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:98607:27"/>
bodies, to preach unto them, who had been diſobedient in the days of <hi>Noah:</hi> this is the vain conceit of moſt people from thoſe words of <hi>Peter,</hi> who ſaith, <hi>By which he went and preached unto the ſpirits in priſon,</hi> as if the ſpirits of the diſobedient peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in the days of <hi>Noah</hi> had been in priſon in ſome local place in the earth without bodies, who had been departed in the days of <hi>Noah,</hi> in the deſtruction of the world by water.</p>
               <p>This the imagination of reaſon in man doth imagine, that ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits may be ſhut up in priſon without bodies, and that the quickening ſpirit of Chriſt might preach unto them without a body.</p>
               <p>But the true light and revelation of faith doth know to the contrary, that no ſpirits can have any being at a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l without bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, neither of God, Angels, nor Man, nor no other living creature, who hath the breath of life in it.</p>
               <p>But to give the interpretation of this Scripture, that the Reader may underſtand, it is thus; the ſpirit of Chriſt, that quickened from the dead to life again, I ſay, is the ſame ſpirit that preached to the ſpirits in priſon in the days of <hi>Noah,</hi> and the ſpirits of the diſobedient world were in priſon in their own bodies in the days of <hi>Noah,</hi> as they were when Chriſt came up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on earth, for then he opened the priſon to them that were bound, by preaching glad tidings of freedom to thoſe that were bound, and liberty to thoſe ſpirits that were in capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity.</p>
               <p>Now (as I ſaid before) this captivity is ſpiritual captivity, and to be bound and in priſon, it is meant a ſpiritual impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the mind, and not a natural impriſonment of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. And this I ſay, the very ſame ſpirit of Chriſt that preached to the Jews when he was upon earth, did preach to the old world in the days of <hi>Noah,</hi> though in a twofold manner.</p>
               <p>And as the ſpirits of men were in priſon in their own igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, blindneſs and darkneſs of underſtandings, in that they were led captives and priſoners by their wicked and unnatural luſts in the days of <hi>Noah:</hi> ſo were both Jews and Gentiles in the days of Chriſt when on earth, their ſpirits were led captive,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:98607:27"/>
and into the priſon of unbelief and perſecution of the Lord of Life, in that their fathers perſecuted the Lords Prophets and Meſſengers he did ſend; ſo did theſe Jews perſecute the Lord himſelf, when he preached to their ſpirits that were in priſon, and led captives by their wicked murdering wills into the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of unbelief; for he did preach when on earth, that whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever did believe in him ſhould be ſaved. And as many as did truly believe in him, their ſpirits were brought out of that ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptivity of unbelief, and out of the priſon of darkneſs in the mind, into a glorious liberty and light of life eternal. And thus did the preaching of Chriſts ſpirit deliver many ſpirits of men and women out of priſon, in the days when he was upon earth.</p>
               <p>So likewiſe this quickening ſpirit of Chriſt; it preached unto the ſpirits in priſon in the days of <hi>Noah.</hi> And why were their ſpirits in priſon in the days of <hi>Noah?</hi> Becauſe they were diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient. And how may they be ſaid to be diſobedient? Becauſe they did not believe that good man <hi>Noah,</hi> who was a preacher of righteouſneſs. And how did he preach righteouſneſs unto that wicked people? In that he prepared the Ark, and being ſo many as a hundred years in building, all that while God is ſaid to wait for their repentance, and that they might believe that God would deſtroy the world by water.</p>
               <p>But inſtead of repentance and believing they hardened their hearts, and mocked at <hi>Noah</hi> and the Ark; ſo that while the Ark was preparing, God waited for the peoples repentance; and all that while that <hi>Noah</hi> was building he preached to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, that the world would be drowned.</p>
               <p>And the ſpirit of Chriſt, which is the ſpirit of God, which was put to death in the fleſh, but quickened by the ſpirit, by which he went and preached unto the ſpirits in priſon in the days of <hi>Noah,</hi> it was the ſame ſpirit that inſtructed <hi>Noah</hi> to build the Ark; ſo that the building of the Ark by <hi>Noah,</hi> he being a Preacher of righteouſneſs, in that he believed God, and built it as the ſpirit of God had commanded and inſtructed him, as God did <hi>Moſes,</hi> ſhewed him the pate<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n of the tabernacle in the Mount.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:98607:28"/>And in as much as <hi>Noah</hi> did obey the commandment of the Lord, according as the ſpirit of the Lord did reveal unto him, <hi>Noah</hi> may be ſaid to be a Preacher of righteouſneſs; and he doing all things by inſpiration of the ſpirit of Chriſt, which was not at that time made of fleſh, but in the fulneſs of time became pure humane fleſh, and ſuffered the pains of death. And the ſame ſpirit that ſuffered death, that very ſame ſpirit that quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, was that ſpirit that preached to the ſpirits in priſon in the days of <hi>Noah,</hi> as aforeſaid.</p>
               <p>And the making of the Ark by the inſpiration of Gods ſpirit in the ſight of the people, who were in priſon in ignorance and darkneſs of mind, is called by the revelation of faith, A preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the ſpirits in priſon: ſo that the ſpirit of God in <hi>Noah</hi> may be ſaid to preach unto thoſe ſpirits in priſon, in the days of <hi>Noah,</hi> and that there was but eight perſons ſaved from the Floud.</p>
               <p>So that this place of Scripture doth no way prove, that the ſpirit of Chriſt did ever preach to ſpirits in priſon without bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies; neither did Chriſts ſpirit preach in the days of <hi>Noah</hi> without a body, for he always preached with a body himſelf, or elſe choſe men that have bodies, and gave them power to preach to ſpirits in priſon, and to deliver the captives, and to ſet the priſoner at liberty, and the bound in priſon to go free.</p>
               <p>So that the Reader may ſee how and in what manner the ſpirit of Chriſt did preach unto the ſpirits in priſon in the days of <hi>Noah,</hi> and how their ſpirits may be ſaid to be in priſon, and how their unbelief in the days of <hi>Noah</hi> was called diſobedience to the preaching of <hi>Noah</hi> all that while the Ark was building. And being built by the inſpiration of the ſpirit of God, it may and is called the preaching of Chriſts ſpirit to them that were in priſon in ſpiritual darkneſs in their minds; for their minds being darkened, they did thoſe things that were unſeemly, yea unnatural, as the people of <hi>Sodom</hi> did. Now, were not the ſpirits of theſe people in priſon, and led captive of thoſe unna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:98607:28"/>
luſts, I think no ſober man will deny; yet theſe were thoſe ſpirits in priſon that Chriſts ſpirit preached unto in the body of <hi>Noah,</hi> in the days of <hi>Noah;</hi> and that there was but eight perſons in the days of <hi>Noah,</hi> that were ſaved from the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction by water, by the preaching of that ſpirit of God in <hi>Noah.</hi> This is the true interpretation and meaning of thoſe words of <hi>Peter</hi> the Apoſtle aforementioned; and how the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Chriſt went and preached unto the ſpirits in priſon in the days of <hi>Noah.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XIII.</head>
               <p>AGain, there are ſome other places of Scripture, which ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral people have objected, as if the ſpirit or ſoul of man might go out of the body, and ſubſiſt in bliſs and happineſs, or in miſery and a tormented condition, without its body it al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways lived in; from that place <hi>Luke</hi> 23.43. Jeſus ſaid to the Thief on the croſs, <hi>Verily I ſay unto thee, This day ſhalt thou be with me in paradiſe.</hi> Now obſerve, this no way proves that the Thiefs ſoul went out of his body into a Paradiſical place, and ſo eſcaped ſuffering death, or did not die; for if the ſoul of Chriſt did die at that time, as is clear by Scripture it did, then the ſoul and life of the Thief did die alſo.</p>
               <p>Then where was the Paradiſe the Thiefs ſoul, and Chriſts ſoul that was heavy unto death, where did they go? To this I ſay, they went to a place of reſt, where all righteous ſouls go, which is to the ſleep of death, for there was nothing did die but the ſouls of them both, and the Paradiſe Chriſt and the Thief went into that day they ſuffered death, I declare it was this, that Chriſt was ſure in himſelf that he ſhould riſe from the dead the third day, and afterward ſhould enter into eternal glory; and this aſſurance in Chriſt that he ſhould riſe again the third day, it was Paradiſe and Peace to his ſoul, that he
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:98607:29"/>
ſhould paſs through that death he was now to ſuffer that ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day into a new life, that ſhould not be capable to die any more.</p>
               <p>So likewiſe when the Thief did truly believe that Jeſus was the Chriſt, the Saviour from eternal death to thoſe that did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, as it is certain he did when he ſaid, <hi>Lord, remember me when thou comeſt into thy kingdom;</hi> for he did really believe, that Chriſt would riſe the third day, and that he would raiſe him to eternal joy and happineſs at the laſt day, and the Thief dying in this faith, he entered into peace of mind, and had reſt and freedom to die in hope and full aſſurance, that Chriſt would raiſe him up ſoul and body to eternal happineſs at the laſt day.</p>
               <p>And this was that Paradiſe that Chriſt and the Thief were in that very day they both ſuffered death; for the aſſurance of everlaſting life in a mans ſelf here in mortality, is the Paradiſe of peace in this life. This I know to be true, and this was the Paradiſe Chriſt did mean the Thief ſhould be in that very day he believed; and not that either of their ſouls went out of their bodies to any other place or Paradiſe, then what was in their own bodies, as aforeſaid.</p>
               <p>In like manner people do imagine that the ſoul of man goeth out of the body at his death, from that ſaying <hi>Acts</hi> 7.59. from thoſe words of <hi>Stepher,</hi> when he was ſtoned to death he ſaid, <hi>Lord Jeſus, receive my ſpirit.</hi> The meaning is this, that when any man dieth in the true faith of Chriſt, in the hope and full aſſurance that Chriſt will raiſe him up to eternal happineſs at the laſt day, he commits his ſpirit into the hands of Chriſt, knowing that though he doth loſe his life for Chriſts ſake here, that Chriſt will raiſe it again, and ſave his ſoul hereafter; and ſo Chriſt may be ſaid to receive his ſpirit. For this I muſt tell the Reader, that there is not a quarter of an hours time to the dead to his riſing again, no not a minute; for there is no time to the dead, not a minute of an hour, though a man have been dead 5000 years, yet it is not a minute of an hour to him that is dead.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:98607:29"/>For all time belongs to the living; for after death there is nothing but eternity, on the other ſide of death either eternal happineſs or eternal miſery: ſo that when men die, they may be ſaid to go immediately to Heaven or to Hell, to joy or tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to be received into Chriſts hands of mercy, or into the hand of Chriſts wrath, where they ſhall be tormented with the Devil and his Angels, yet ſhall never ſee the Devil, nor his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, nor themſelves, to eternity; as they did not know the Devil here, neither ſhall they know or ſee him hereafter, yet be tormented with him.</p>
               <p>And in this ſenſe a faithful ſpirit or ſoul, as <hi>Stephen</hi> was may be ſaid to commit his ſpirit into the hands of Chriſt, and that Chriſt doth receive his ſpirit into his hands, and will raiſe it up at the laſt day, which will not be a minute of an hours time to the dead, as I ſaid before; therefore let not the ſeed of faith think the time long between death and the ſalvation of their ſouls, becauſe ſo many of the faithful have been ſo many hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred years in the grave: and let not the wicked unbelieving people comfort themſelves, that the dead ſhall never riſe again, becauſe the Fathers are dead, and the Prophets are dead, and we ſee none of them riſe again, therefore we conclude their ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits are gone to Heaven without bodies, and the ſpirits of the wicked are gone to Hell without bodies, but as minute of an hours time will deſide this matter, when the dead are raiſed: for they ſhall not remember they have been aſleep in the duſt one minute of an ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r, for there is no remembrance of time in the grave. Therefore let that vain conceit that is in moſt people fall, of ſpirits going to God without bodies, for I can aſſure you there is no ſuch thing neither can there be any true peace in that conceit; I know it by faith now, and by experience, for I was of that opinion once my ſelf, when I was zealous in religion accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Puritan way but I knew no Scripture truly, neither was there one true Interpreter of Scripture, no not one in thoſe days, that could ſhew, a man the true righteouſneſs of God, or the true way to everlaſting life.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:98607:30"/>
               <head>CHAP. XIV.</head>
               <p>THere is another place of Scripture that is objected, that ſeems is if the ſoul went out of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> body when they die; as in 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 17.21. where <hi>Elijah</hi> prayed, that <hi>the childs ſoul might come into him again.</hi> The meaning is this, that <hi>Elijah</hi> did pray in faith unto God, that he would aſſiſt him in this as in other things, as i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſhutting up the Heavens that it ſhould not rain, and calling for fire from Heaven to deſtroy thoſe two captains and their fitties, and m ny other wonderful things he did; ſo he pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto God to ſtrengthen his faith, ſo that he might have pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to raiſe this childs life out of death again.</p>
               <p>Therefore he ſtretched himſelf upon the child, and prayed that the childs ſoul might come into him again, that is, that the childs ſoul or life might quicken in the body of the child again; for <hi>Elijah</hi> knew the ſoul of the child was dead, and by the warm fleſh of the Prophet laid upon the childs dead fleſh, and the faith and prayer of the Prophet together, it begot life in the child again, ſo that the ſoul that was dead it became life in the child again, and that life that was quickened, it run through the veins of the childs body, and ſo the childs ſoul did come into him again.</p>
               <p>For this I ſay, if the ſoul of the child had been gone out of the body, then <hi>Elijah</hi> did not raiſe the dead child to life again; for how can a man be ſaid to be dead, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nas life doth not die, but ſlips out of the body, as moſt people do vainly imagine; but it may be clear to thoſe whoſe underſtanding are enlightened, that <hi>Elijah</hi> did raiſe the child from death to life, and that the childs ſoul was dead in its body, and that the ſoul of the child was revived in the childs body again by the power of faith in <hi>Elijah.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:98607:30"/>And the very ſame thing was done by the Prophet <hi>Eliſha,</hi> as in 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 4.34. the Prophet <hi>Eliſha</hi> did the ſame thing to the <hi>Shunamite</hi> womans ſon, he <hi>went up, and lay upon the child, and put his mouth upon his mouth, and his eyes upon his eyes, and his hands upon his hands, and he ſtretched himſelf upon the child; and the fleſh of the child waxed warm, and Eliſha ſtretched himſelf up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the child a ſecond time:</hi> here the Reader may ſee, that the child was dead, and by the faith and prayer, and by the warm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Prophet <hi>Eliſha</hi> his fleſh, the child revived to life a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain both body and ſoul. And <hi>Eliſha</hi> did uſe the ſame means and way as <hi>Elijah</hi> did; for he went in, and ſhut the door, and prayed unto the Lord as <hi>Elijah</hi> did, and ſtretched himſelf upon the child as <hi>Elijah</hi> did, and raiſed the child to life again by the power of faith.</p>
               <p>Yet <hi>Eliſha</hi> maketh no mention of the ſoul coming into the child again, but he delivered the body and ſoul of the child, that were both dead together, he delivered them both alive together to the childs mother. It was the ſame thing done by <hi>Elijah,</hi> onely ſome difference in the words, but the ſenſe and meaning is all one.</p>
               <p>So that the Reader may underſtand, if any true light of life be in him, that the ſoul of the child went not out of its body, but died in the body; and by the power of faith in the Prophet it quickned alive out of death in the childs body again; for the ſoul or life of the child never went out of the body, as is vainly imagined; but the ſoul, life, and ſpirit of the child was abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely dead in the body, and by the power of faith in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet the dead ſoul or life of the child was quickened alive again, and cauſed the body to live alſo. For if the woman ſhould have had the ſoul of the child given unto her without the body, ſhe would have given the Prophet no thanks for raiſing her childs ſoul without a body; but the body and ſoul being one perſon, they were both dead together, and the Prophet raiſed them both together alive, and the woman received them both toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and rejoyced greatly in God, and gave honour to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:98607:31"/>Thus in ſhort I have given the true interpretation of all thoſe Scriptures that moſt ſeem, or moſt commonly are object<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed againſt the mortality of the ſoul, or to prove that ſpirits do go out of the body at the time of death, or that ſpirits may be raiſed without bodies, or have any being without bodies, and that a ſpirit may appear in a ſhape without a body, or that a ſpirit can aſſume what ſhape it pleaſe, yet have no body or ſubſtance.</p>
               <p>Theſe things the vain imagination of reaſon in man hath cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated in it ſelf, to fright it ſelf with, for there is no ſuch thing as ſpirits walking without bodies, neither doth any ſpirit go out of the body when men die, as is imagined by moſt people; but theſe are factions of mens brains, created by the imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the dark minds of men and women, for God never created any ſuch thing, as I have ſhewed before.</p>
               <p>And as for that ſaying of <hi>Solomon, Eccl.</hi> 12.7. <hi>Then ſhall the duſt return to the earth as it was, and the ſpirit ſhall return to God who gave it.</hi> His meaning (I ſuppoſe) in theſe words is, as is generally conceived by all people, the body to the duſt, and the ſpirit returns to God that gave it when men die: but theſe ſayings of <hi>Solomon</hi> are no Scripture, for <hi>Solomon</hi> was no Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture writer, for his writings were not written by the revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of faith, but by the revelation of reaſon; yet it was the pureſt of reaſon, and he had the greateſt meaſure of the wiſdom of reaſon, and the knowledge of nature, of any that was before him ſince <hi>Adam,</hi> or any that ſhall come after him.</p>
               <p>Therefore God choſe him King, and gave him the pureſt wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of reaſon, according to his deſire in his prayer to God, that his wiſdom might reſemble Heaven for glory, as it did; for what glory could a King have upon earth greater then he had? which was a true reſemblance of the glory of Heaven; and this glory was procured by that power and great wiſdom of reaſon in him; yet for all this he was ignorant of the revelation of faith, and of ſpiritual and heavenly things, ignorant of the true God, and of the right Devil, and of ſome things in Nature.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:98607:31"/>As that the ſpirit of a man ſhould return to God that gave it without a body; when as God never gave any ſpirit to man without a body, nor to no other creature: but <hi>Solomon</hi> being ignorant, that the ſpirit or ſoul of man is generated and begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by the law of generation as well as the body; this was in the creation when God made man in his own image, the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of this cauſed him to ſpeak thus; for he knew not where the ſpirit went when the body is laid in the earth, no more then the learned Philoſophers do, who ſay, A ſpirit cannot die; as if the ſpirit and life of every creature were the ſpirit or life of God, elſe they think no creature could move and have a being.</p>
               <p>And though <hi>Solomon</hi> was a wiſe man, as the Heathen Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers were wiſe men in nature; yet they were all ignorant in this one thing, of the law of generation or procreation, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe and multiply, as God hath placed in nature, when he created the world in the beginning; for every creature as well as man were to increaſe and multiply by the law of generation; and this I am ſure, they begot ſpirit, life, and ſoul by generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as well as bodies.</p>
               <p>But if it be objected, that God breathed into man the breath of life, and he became a living ſoul; and ſo mans ſpirit is of a more noble divine life or ſpirit then any other crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</p>
               <p>To this I ſay; the law of generation to increaſe and multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, was placed in mans ſeed and nature by God the creator, as in other creatures: for this is to be obſerved, that <hi>Adam</hi> did not come to be a living ſoul by generation, as we do ever ſince; but he and <hi>Eve</hi> were firſt made as a foundation for generation; ſo that God made or created but one man and one woman, all men and women that have been generated and begotten ever ſince, cannot properly be ſaid to be made nor created, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten by generation; for God never made and created but one man and one woman, all others are generated and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:98607:32"/>Therefore when man begets a ſon or daughter in the way of generation, he begets the ſoul or ſpirit of the child as well as the body; and the ſoul or ſpirit came out of the mans loins as well as the body: as it was ſaid by <hi>Jacob, Seventy ſouls came out of his loins;</hi> if ſo, then that ſpirit or ſoul that is begotten by generation, it muſt and doth die: for this I ſay, God never breathed the breath of life into no man, but into <hi>Adam:</hi> the ſpirit of life in all men and women elſe or ſince have been gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated and begotten; and what ſpirit and ſoul of man that is ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerated, it doth die and turn to duſt, till the regeneration, when God ſhall rai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e it again, which will not be a minute of an hour to the dead ſpirit, as I ſaid before. So it may be clear to thoſe that have the true light of faith in them, that the ſoul or ſpirit of man doth die as well as the body: they both came into the world together alive, and they ſhall both go out of the world again dead, as I have ſhewed before. Alſo the Reader may ſee, that thoſe Scriptures have been miſunderſtood through the ignorance and darkneſs of mens minds, to think that the ſoul or ſpirit of man doth not die, but ſlips out of the body; but to imagine that ſpirits may walk without bodies, or that any Witch can raiſe any ſpirit without a body; and many other conceits that do ariſe out of the dark mind of man, which have been grounded upon thoſe Scripture-words; therefore I have given the interpretation of all thoſe places of Scripture that are of moſt concernment, and ſeem to bear ſuch a ſenſe, as is ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally conceived among profeſſors of the Scriptures: ſo that whoever underſtands the interpretation, may receive great ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction in their minds in this point, ſo much for the ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the underſtanding in heart, and for the diſcontent of the ignorant and dark-minded people, who believe by tradition that their ſpirits do not die, but ſlide out of the body at the time of death; and if they have been evil and wicked livers, their ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits do walk afterwards, and cannot be at reſt. Theſe conceits have been exceeding brief in the world heretofore, when people were in darkneſs, and ſo it is ſtill where the darkneſs of mind ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:98607:32"/>
               <head>CHAP. XV.</head>
               <p>THere is one thing more that would be neceſſary for the wiſe in heart to know, which the Scriptures ſpeak of in ſeveral places; but I never heard any of the Miniſtry tell what that Satan is the Scriptures ſpeak of, therefore I ſhall ſpeak a word or two to ſhew what Satan is, and ſo conclude. 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 21.1. <hi>And Sathan ſtood up againſt Iſrael;</hi> and <hi>Job</hi> 1.6. <hi>And Satan came alſo among them;</hi> and chap. 21.22. <hi>And the Lord ſaid to Sathan, From whence comeſt thou? And God ſaid to Sathan, Haſt thou conſidered my ſervant Job? Ezek.</hi> 3.1. <hi>And Sathan ſtanding at his right hand. Mat.</hi> 16.23. <hi>Get thee behind me, Sathan. Luke</hi> 10.18. <hi>I beheld Sathan as lightening fall from Heaven.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 21.1. <hi>And Sathan ſtood up againſt Iſrael, and provoked David to number Iſrael.</hi> This Sathan that provoked <hi>David,</hi> it was the motions of reaſon in himſelf, being lifted up in his own mind, in that he had overcome the children of <hi>Amon,</hi> he thought to make nothing of the <hi>Philiſtins;</hi> therefore the thoughts of his heart moved him to number the people, to know his ſtrength. And this motion that did ariſe in his heart, it was Satan, it is called Satan, becauſe thoſe motions proceed from the ſpirit or ſeed of reaſon in him. In 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24.1. it is ſaid, <hi>The anger of the Lord was kindled againſt Iſrael, and he moved David againſt them to ſay, Go, number Iſrael:</hi> that is, the Lord ſuffered the motions of reaſon in <hi>David</hi> to be powerful and ſtrong in him, that no arguments ſhould diſſwade him from it, but the people muſt be numbered; and this was that Satan in <hi>David,</hi> and no ſpirit without him.</p>
               <p>So <hi>Job.</hi> 1.6. <hi>The ſons of God came to preſent themſelves before the Lord, and Satan c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>me alſo among them.</hi> To this I ſay, the
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:98607:33"/>
book of <hi>Job</hi> is no Scripture, neither are men to build their faith upon it, becauſe the book of <hi>Job</hi> was written before <hi>Moſes,</hi> therefore no Scripture; for <hi>Moſes</hi> his writing is the firſt foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tion of Scripture. Yet this I do confeſs, that <hi>Job</hi> was a good and faithful man; and becauſe he was afflicted by Satan, and Satan is ſpoken of in ſeveral places of Scripture, yet none of them did declare what this Satan is, therefore I ſhall declare now what that Satan was, that came among the ſons of God.</p>
               <p>I declare the ſons of God they were the ſons of <hi>Job,</hi> who feaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their three ſiſters, as you may read. They were called the ſons of God, becauſe they were that good and faithful man <hi>Jobs</hi> ſons; as the ſons of <hi>Seth</hi> were called the ſons of God, and <hi>they looked upon the daughters of men, and ſaw that they were fair, &amp;c.</hi> as you may read in <hi>Geneſis.</hi> Now that Satan came amongſt them when they preſented themſelves before the Lord, it was the ſpirit of reaſon in <hi>Jobs</hi> ſeven ſons, when they feaſted their three ſiſters, they were moved in their minds to voluptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, drunkenneſs, and luſt, as the reſt of the Heathen were where they lived; ſo that they did wickedneſs in the abſence of <hi>Job</hi> their father: and <hi>Job</hi> fearing in their wickedneſs his ſons had curſed God in their hearts, as you may ſee in the verſe before. So <hi>Job</hi> cauſed his ſons to preſent themſelves before the Lord, and to worſhip the Lord, as it was the manner for <hi>Job</hi> to do in thoſe times, and Satan came with them, that is, the ſpirit of reaſon in his ſons came with them, reaſoning in themſelves, why ſhould their father <hi>Job</hi> reprove them for their wickedneſs in their feaſts; this was that Satan that came a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, for he was in them, and no other Satan but what was within them.</p>
               <p>And this is that Satan that goeth to and fro in the earth, to tempt and deſtroy thoſe that are faithful: ſo that this ſpirit of reaſon, this Satan, it goeth to and fro in the earth, to tempt and deſtroy the faithful.</p>
               <p>It was that Satan that did motion the <hi>Sabeans</hi> and <hi>Chalde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> to take away <hi>Jobs</hi> oxen, and ſlay his ſervants as they were
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:98607:33"/>
plowing; and fired the ſheep, and burnt up <hi>Jobs</hi> ſervants; and the <hi>Chaldæans</hi> came with a band of men, ſeeing <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>b</hi> ſmitten and deſtroyed by the <hi>Sabeans;</hi> and they came with three bands of men, and deſtroyed the camels and the reſt of his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants.</p>
               <p>For this muſt be minded, that in thoſe times there was no Law to deliver or help the innocent, but he that had the ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt ſword carried the day. And the Lord for trial of <hi>Jobs</hi> faith and patience, and for a patern for the ages to come, he ſuffered the ſpirit of unclean reaſon in the <hi>Sabeans</hi> and <hi>Chaldæans</hi> to go to and fro in the earth, to ſtir up their people to deſtroy <hi>Job</hi> and all his houſe and cattel.</p>
               <p>Alſo God ſuffered the natural wind to blow down the houſe where <hi>Jobs</hi> ſons were feaſting, and deſtroyed them according to the deſire of the ſpirit of unclean reaſon in the <hi>Sabeans</hi> and <hi>Chaldæans.</hi> For the ſons of <hi>Job</hi> were wicked children, though called the ſons of God.</p>
               <p>And laſt of all the ſpirit of unclean reaſon in <hi>Jobs</hi> wife was that Satan that tempted <hi>Job</hi> to curſe God and die: ſo that there is no other ſpirit or Satan without man: but that Satan ſpoken of in <hi>Job,</hi> it was the ſpirit of unclean reaſon in the minds of the <hi>Sabeans, Chaldaæeans,</hi> and in <hi>Jobs</hi> wife and ſons; that was that Satan, and no other.</p>
               <p>And as for thoſe diſputes God had with Satan, and Satan with God; it was nothing elſe but the motions of <hi>Jobs</hi> heart paſſing through his troubled ſoul, the ſeed of faith diſputed in him for God, perſuading him to be patient, and let that have its perfect work, and ſo hope did increaſe in him; and the ſeed of reaſon, which was Satan in him as well as in others, it plead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed againſt God, reaſoning in him as if God did not do well or juſtly by him, that had been ſo righteous in his life, one who never did no wrong to his neighbour, but always fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ed God; yet that God ſhould ſuffer the wicked to deſtroy his cattel and ſervants, and ſuffer the wind to blow down his houſe, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy his children; and not onely ſo, but ſuffer his body to break out with boils and botches moſt lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>thſom, as if he had been the greateſt ſinner in the world; ſo that he thought that
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:98607:34"/>
God dealt more cruelly with him then with any other crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. And further, he thought God dealt hardly with him, that he would neither take away his life, that he might die out of this troubled mind and pains of body, nor reſtore him to health. Theſe and ſuch like reaſonings and thoughts paſſed through <hi>Jobs</hi> troubled ſoul, even from the ſpirit or ſeed of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in him, which is the diſpute of Satan: for as the ſeed of faith in <hi>Job</hi> diſputed for God, ſo did the ſeed of reaſon in <hi>Job</hi> diſpute for Satan; for there is no other Satan but what is in man, as I ſaid before.</p>
               <p>So in <hi>Zach.</hi> 3.1. here <hi>Zachariah</hi> the Prophet ſaw in a viſion the redempttion of the ſeed of faith by Chriſt under the type of <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhua</hi> the High prieſt, ſtanding before the Angel of the Lord, and Satan ſtanding at his right hand to reſiſt him. This High prieſt was Chriſt cloathed with filthy garments, when he became fleſh, when on eaeth he appeared unto men, to be clothed in filthy garments, being ſo mean, and h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d not a place to lay his head, yet profeſſed himſelf to be the Son of God, the High prieſt that ſhould offer up himſelf for to ſave his people; for High prieſts in former times did appear to the people with rich and glorious garments; but this High prieſt doth appear to the ſeed of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, to be clothed in filthy garments, not fit (as reaſon thinks) to ſtand before the Angel of the Lord.</p>
               <p>And this Satan that ſtands at his right hand to reſiſt him, it was the ſpirit of unclean reaſon in thoſe people of the Jews when Chriſt was upon earth, and when that Devi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that tempted Chriſt, ſpoken of in <hi>Matthew,</hi> diſputed with Chriſt, he reſiſted the High prieſt, and ſtood at Chriſts right hand at that time; and this Devil that tempted Chriſt, it was a man endued with an high pitch of reaſon, and that ſpirit of reaſon, or wiſdom of reaſon, in that man that tempted Chriſt the High prieſt, it was Satan that ſtrove to reſiſt Chriſt in diſpute, whereupon Chriſt ſaid, <hi>Get thee hence Satan.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Satan was a man, and the ſpirit of reaſon in this man, is that Satan that always reſiſteth the wiſdom of faith, which is the wiſdom of God. But this hath been more largely treated
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:98607:34"/>
upon in our other writings, ſo I ſhall ſpeak no mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e of that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil and his temptations here.</p>
               <p>So in <hi>Matth.</hi> 16.23. Chriſt ſaid unto <hi>Peter, Get thee behind me Satan.</hi> Here you ſee <hi>Peter</hi> is called Satan, becauſe it was the ſpirit of reaſon in <hi>Peter</hi> that ſaid, Maſter, pity thy ſelf: that is, the thoughts of <hi>Peters</hi> heart they did ſavour of the fleſhly part, that is, thoſe motions to perſuade Chriſt to ſave himſelf from death, they did ariſe from the ſeed of reaſon in <hi>Peter,</hi> therefore called Satan; for there was no new ſpirit that came into <hi>Peter</hi> at that time, to cauſe him to ſpeak thoſe words, but thoſe words proceeded from the ſeed of reaſon in him, as aforeſaid, therefore called Satan.</p>
               <p>And whereſoever that expreſſion is uſed, as <hi>Peter</hi> ſaid him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in the <hi>Acts, Why hath Satan filled thine heart to lie unto the Holy Ghoſt?</hi> that is, why hath the motions of reaſon in thee perſuaded thy heart to tell a lie unto us, that have the Holy Ghoſt in us?</p>
               <p>So the Reader may clearly ſee, that there is no other Satan to tempt God or Man, but the motions and words that proceed from the ſeed of reaſon in man and woman.</p>
               <p>So in <hi>Luke</hi> 10.18. <hi>And Chriſt ſaid unto his diſciples, I beheld Satan as lightening fall from heaven.</hi> This Chriſt ſpake, becauſe his diſciples rejoyced that the Devils were ſubject to them. The meaning of Chriſt was, that he ſaw the ſpirit of reaſon, that was in the Rulers of the Jews, very high in the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> even as if they were in Heaven, think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in themſelves that none could be more happy and ſurer of Heaven and peace with God, then they that kept to the Law of <hi>Moſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now Chriſt knowing that this righteouſneſs of the Jews ſhould be thrown down by the righteouſneſs of faith, which his Apoſtles ſhould pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch, therefore he ſaw by faith that the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of reaſon in the Rulers of the Jews ſhould fall like lightening from Heaven; and ſo it did, and the diſciples of Chriſt ſhould, by the doctrine and righteouſneſs of faith, tread upon ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents, and upon their perſecution, and upon their righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:98607:35"/>
of the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and upon all that which did fall like lightening from Heaven; they ſhould tread upon Satan, that is, upon the very wiſdom of reaſon the Devil.</p>
               <p>This is the true meaning of Chriſt, when he beheld Satan fall from Heaven like lightening, and what Satan is ſo much ſpoken of in Scripture. Much more might be ſaid to enlarge this point, but I have ſpoken more already then I did intend; but I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe there is enough written here in ſhort to ſatisfie thoſe, that can underſtand by a little what a great deal means. And alſo people may know when they ſpeak of Satan what Satan is, and when they ſpeak of the Devil, they may know what the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil is.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>So much concerning the interpretation of Satan, and the concluſion of this Epiſtle, written by <hi>Lodowick Muggleton.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:98607:38"/>
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:98607:38"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:98607:39"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:98607:39"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:98607:40"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:98607:40"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:98607:41"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:98607:41"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:98607:42"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:98607:42"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:98607:43"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:98607:43"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:98607:44"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:98607:44"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:98607:45"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:98607:45"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:98607:46"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:98607:46"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:98607:47"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:98607:47"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
